<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:36:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of four cold Jupiters through combined analyses of radial velocity and astrometry data</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11280v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11280v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Yiyun Wu et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine if we could only see the shadow of a person walking by a streetlight, never the person themselves. That's essentially how astronomers have been finding planets around other stars—detecting their subtle effects rather than seeing them directly. This research represents a major step forward in our ability to understand distant worlds, particularly "cold Jupiters"—giant planets that orbit far from their host stars, much like our own Jupiter. These distant giants are crucial pieces in the cosmic puzzle of how planetary systems form and evolve, yet we've found surprisingly few of them. Understanding why could reshape our knowledge of how common solar systems like ours really are.
What They Did
The researchers combined two different planet-hunting techniques to get a more complete picture of these distant worlds. First, they used the "wobble method," which detects how a planet's gravity causes its host star to move slightly back and forth. Second, they analyzed precise measurements of star positions from the European Space Agency's Gaia spacecraft, which can detect the tiny shifts in a star's position caused by an orbiting planet. By combining data spanning 25 years and using sophisticated computer modeling, they could determine not just that planets exist, but also their actual masses and the shapes of their orbits—information that's usually difficult or impossible to obtain.
Key Findings
The team discovered four new cold Jupiter planets orbiting distant stars. Two of these worlds are the first planets ever confirmed in their respective systems. The most impressive find is a Jupiter-like planet that takes over 21 years to complete one orbit—the longest orbital period ever found for a planet in this mass range. These planets range from about one-third the mass of Jupiter to over five times Jupiter's mass, showing the diversity of giant worlds that exist beyond our solar system.
Looking Forward
This research demonstrates that many more cold Jupiters are likely waiting to be discovered as our technology improves. Some of these newly found worlds may even be candidates for direct imaging with next-generation telescopes, potentially allowing us to study their atmospheres and compositions directly—a major leap toward understanding planetary formation throughout the galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aligned, Misaligned and Polar Orbits of Hot Jupiters: Measuring Spin-Orbit Angles via Doppler Tomography with HARPS-N</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11313v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11313v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Z. Balkóová et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine spinning a basketball on your finger while a marble orbits around it. Now picture that marble's orbit tilted at a crazy angle—maybe even going over the poles instead of around the equator. This bizarre scenario actually happens with some of the most extreme planets we've discovered: hot Jupiters. These are gas giant planets that orbit incredibly close to their stars, completing a full year in just days. By measuring how tilted these planetary orbits are compared to their star's rotation, astronomers can piece together the violent history of how these worlds ended up in such extreme locations. It's like being a cosmic detective, using clues from today to understand dramatic events that happened billions of years ago.
What They Did
The researchers used a technique called Doppler tomography to study three hot Jupiter systems. Think of it like taking an X-ray of starlight. When a planet crosses in front of its star, it blocks light from different parts of the star's surface as it moves. Since stars rotate, different parts move toward or away from us at different speeds, slightly changing the color of their light. By carefully analyzing these tiny color changes during planetary transits, scientists can map how the planet's orbit is oriented relative to the star's spin. The team used three different computer programs to analyze their data, ensuring their results were reliable and not dependent on any single method.
Key Findings
The three planets showed dramatically different orbital orientations. HAT-P-49 b orbits over its star's poles—imagine the marble going from north pole to south pole instead of around the equator. HAT-P-57A b follows a perfectly normal equatorial orbit, like planets in our solar system. Most intriguingly, XO-3A b sits at a 38-degree tilt, occupying a middle ground that few hot Jupiters inhabit. This is like finding a planet that's neither perfectly aligned nor completely sideways—a rare configuration that challenges our understanding of planetary migration.
Looking Forward
These findings add crucial pieces to the puzzle of hot Jupiter formation. The diversity of orientations suggests multiple pathways brought these planets so close to their stars—some migrated gently through their birth disks, others were violently scattered by gravitational interactions. Understanding these processes helps astronomers predict what kinds of planetary systems exist throughout our galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KMT-2025-BLG-1616Lb: First Microlensing Bound Planet From DREAMS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11469v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11469v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Hongjing Yang et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to spot a firefly buzzing around a lighthouse from thousands of miles away—that's essentially what astronomers face when hunting for planets orbiting distant stars. Most exoplanet detection methods only work for massive planets orbiting close to their stars, leaving smaller, more distant worlds largely invisible. This research demonstrates a powerful technique called microlensing that can find these elusive planets, including ones that might be similar to Earth or Mars. Understanding what types of planets exist throughout our galaxy helps us piece together how planetary systems form and whether Earth-like worlds are common or rare.
What They Did
The team used a cosmic magnifying glass effect called gravitational microlensing. When a star passes directly in front of another star from our perspective, its gravity bends light like a lens, temporarily brightening the background star. If the foreground star has a planet, it creates a distinctive blip in this brightening pattern—like a signature that reveals the planet's presence. Two telescope networks worked together: the Korea Microlensing Telescope Network spotted the initial signal, while the DECam Rogue Earths and Mars Survey (DREAMS) took ultra-frequent observations—one measurement per minute—to capture crucial details that resolved ambiguities in the data.
Key Findings
The researchers discovered a Neptune-sized planet roughly 40 times more massive than Earth, orbiting a small red dwarf star about one-third the mass of our Sun. The planet sits approximately 1.6 times farther from its star than Earth does from the Sun, and the entire system lies about 7,500 light-years away toward the center of our galaxy. This marks the first planet discovery for the DREAMS survey, proving the technique works exceptionally well for finding smaller worlds.
Looking Forward
This success suggests DREAMS could detect free-floating planets—worlds ejected from their star systems and wandering alone through space. The survey appears sensitive enough to spot Mars-sized wanderers and possibly even Moon-sized objects, opening an entirely new window into planetary populations across our galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of disc photoevaporation on the long-term evolution of giant planets in mean motion resonances</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10811v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10811v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Emmanuel J. Greenfield, James E. Owen</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine two massive planets locked in a cosmic dance, orbiting their star in perfect synchronization—one completes exactly two orbits for every three of its neighbor, like clockwork that's been running for millions of years. These "resonant" relationships are surprisingly common among the thousands of exoplanets we've discovered, but scientists have struggled to understand how they form and why some survive while others fall apart. This research tackles a crucial missing piece of the puzzle: how intense stellar radiation that strips away the gas disk around young stars affects these delicate planetary partnerships. Understanding this process helps us decode the life stories of planetary systems and explains why we see such diverse arrangements of worlds beyond our solar system.
What They Did
The researchers created detailed computer simulations to watch planetary systems evolve over millions of years. They modeled young star systems where two giant planets (similar to Jupiter) orbit in lockstep while embedded in a disk of gas and dust. In their virtual laboratory, they cranked up the intensity of a process called photoevaporation—where the star's intense radiation essentially boils away the surrounding gas disk. They tested different scenarios by varying the disk's mass, how thick or thin the gas was, the planets' weights, and how tightly synchronized the planetary orbits were. Think of it like running multiple experiments to see how different cooking temperatures and ingredient amounts affect the final recipe.
Key Findings
The results revealed a surprising twist: intense stellar radiation can actually stabilize some planetary partnerships that would otherwise break apart. When radiation strips gas from the space between planets, it reduces the gravitational forces that normally push planets out of sync. This stabilizing effect works best for planets in 3:2 resonances (three orbits to two), which are naturally more fragile. However, the process can backfire for planets in 2:1 resonances (two orbits to one), sometimes destabilizing these normally robust relationships. In all cases, the planets end up with more stretched, oval-shaped orbits rather than circular ones.
Looking Forward
These discoveries help explain the incredible diversity of planetary systems we observe today. The research suggests that a star's radiation environment during a system's youth plays a crucial role in sculpting the final arrangement of planets. This has practical implications for upcoming space missions like the European Space Agency's Gaia telescope, which will measure tiny stellar wobbles caused by orbiting planets. By understanding how these resonant relationships evolve, astronomers can better predict which types of planetary systems to look for and refine their detection strategies, bringing us closer to finding Earth-like worlds in stable, long-lasting orbits.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metal Pipe: A Broadly-Applicable Stellar Abundance Pipeline Using Isochronal Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10794v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10794v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jared R. Kolecki, Lauren M. Weiss</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand different neighborhoods by studying the houses in them—but each house was analyzed by a different inspector using different methods. That's the challenge astronomers face when studying stars that host planets outside our solar system. With thousands of exoplanets discovered, scientists need a consistent way to analyze their host stars across the galaxy. Understanding what these stars are made of helps us learn how planetary systems form and whether they might harbor worlds similar to Earth. This research tackles that challenge by creating a universal tool for analyzing stellar chemistry.
What They Did
Researchers developed a new computer program called "Metal Pipe" that works like a standardized recipe for analyzing stars. The program takes high-quality light measurements from telescopes—essentially stellar fingerprints that reveal what elements are inside each star—and processes them using consistent methods. Think of it as creating a universal translator that can read the chemical signatures of different types of stars, from those slightly smaller than our Sun to those much larger. The team tested their new tool on 503 previously studied stars to make sure it produced reliable results compared to earlier measurements.
Key Findings
The new tool successfully measured ten different chemical elements in stars, including carbon, oxygen, iron, and others that are crucial for planet formation. When compared to previous measurements, Metal Pipe's results were remarkably consistent—temperature measurements differed by only about 100 degrees Kelvin (roughly equivalent to the difference between a warm day and a hot day), while chemical abundance measurements were accurate to within 10% margins. This level of precision means astronomers can now confidently compare stars across large populations.
Looking Forward
This standardized approach will help astronomers build comprehensive catalogs of exoplanet host stars, potentially revealing patterns about which types of stars are most likely to form Earth-like planets. As the tool gets refined for smaller, cooler stars, it could unlock insights about the most common planetary systems in our galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
