<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:57:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of four cold Jupiters through combined analyses of radial velocity and astrometry data</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11280v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11280v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:57:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Yiyun Wu et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand how our solar system formed by only studying Earth and Mars—you'd miss the crucial role that Jupiter played in shaping everything around it. That's exactly the challenge astronomers face when studying distant planetary systems. Jupiter-like planets that orbit far from their stars, called "cold Jupiters," are cosmic architects that influence how entire planetary systems develop. Yet these distant giants are notoriously difficult to spot and study. This research tackles that challenge head-on, uncovering four new cold Jupiters and demonstrating a powerful new method for finding many more. Understanding these distant worlds helps us piece together the story of how planetary systems—including our own—came to be.
What They Did
The researchers combined two detective techniques to hunt for these elusive planets. First, they used radial velocity measurements, which detect the tiny wobble a planet causes as it tugs on its host star—like watching a dog walker get pulled back and forth by an invisible leash. Second, they incorporated data from the Gaia space telescope, which precisely tracks how stars move across the sky over decades. When a star has a hidden planetary companion, its motion becomes slightly erratic, like a person walking while carrying an invisible, shifting weight. By combining these two approaches over a 25-year period, the team could determine not just that planets exist, but their exact masses, orbital tilts, and three-dimensional paths through space.
Key Findings
The team discovered four cold Jupiters, each taking years to decades to complete a single orbit around their stars. The most extreme, dubbed HD 68475 b, takes over 21 years to circle its star and weighs about five times more than Jupiter. Another standout is HD 100508 b, which completes its 15-year orbit while weighing slightly more than Jupiter. Two others were found in multi-planet systems, including one that may be tilted dramatically compared to its planetary neighbor—a configuration that could reveal how planetary systems can become dynamically unstable over time. Remarkably, one of these worlds holds the record for the longest orbital period among planets in its mass range.
Looking Forward
This research opens a new chapter in exoplanet discovery. The success of combining stellar wobbles with precise positional measurements suggests that thousands more cold Jupiters are waiting to be found in existing Gaia data. Some of these newly discovered worlds, particularly HD 68475 b, are prime candidates for direct imaging with next-generation telescopes, potentially allowing astronomers to study their atmospheres and compositions directly. As more cold Jupiters are uncovered, scientists will finally have the large sample sizes needed to solve long-standing mysteries about how these cosmic architects form and sculpt planetary systems across the galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aligned, Misaligned and Polar Orbits of Hot Jupiters: Measuring Spin-Orbit Angles via Doppler Tomography with HARPS-N</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11313v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11313v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:57:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Z. Balkóová et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine throwing a baseball perfectly straight while spinning like a top—that's how we'd expect planets to orbit their stars, moving in the same direction as the star's rotation. But the universe loves to surprise us. Scientists have discovered that many "hot Jupiters"—massive planets that orbit incredibly close to their stars—move in bizarre ways: some travel backward, others loop around their star's poles like a Ferris wheel. These strange orbits hold crucial clues about how planetary systems form and evolve, helping us understand whether our own solar system's neat, orderly arrangement is common or remarkably special.
What They Did
The researchers used a clever technique called Doppler tomography to study three hot Jupiter planets. When a planet passes in front of its star (like a tiny eclipse), it blocks different parts of the star's spinning surface. Since one side of a spinning star moves toward us and the other moves away, this creates a distinctive signature in the star's light—like a shadow moving across the star's face. By carefully analyzing this shadow using three different computer programs and a sensitive instrument called HARPS-N, the scientists could determine exactly how each planet's orbit is tilted compared to its star's rotation. Think of it like figuring out whether a marble rolling around a spinning basketball follows the equator, goes over the poles, or takes some other crazy path.
Key Findings
The three planets showed dramatically different behaviors. HAT-P-57A b is the "well-behaved" one, orbiting almost perfectly aligned with its star's equator. XO-3A b is moderately tilted at 38 degrees—imagine a planet taking a diagonal path around its star. Most remarkably, HAT-P-49 b is nearly polar, orbiting at 85 degrees—essentially going over its star's north and south poles rather than around its equator. This polar orbit is like a planet doing loop-the-loops instead of following a normal circular track.
Looking Forward
These findings add to growing evidence that planetary systems can be far more chaotic than our own solar system suggests. Understanding why some hot Jupiters end up in such extreme orbits helps scientists piece together the violent early histories of planetary systems—including whether planets migrate inward through gentle gravitational interactions or dramatic collisions and ejections. This research brings us closer to answering fundamental questions about how common Earth-like, stable planetary systems truly are in our galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KMT-2025-BLG-1616Lb: First Microlensing Bound Planet From DREAMS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11469v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11469v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:57:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Hongjing Yang et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to spot a firefly dancing around a lighthouse beam from thousands of miles away—that's essentially what astronomers face when hunting for planets beyond our solar system. Most exoplanets are discovered when they pass directly in front of their host stars, but this method only works for planets whose orbits align perfectly with our view from Earth. This new research demonstrates a completely different technique called gravitational microlensing, which can detect planets we'd never find otherwise. It's like having a cosmic magnifying glass that reveals hidden worlds, opening up entirely new regions of space for planet hunting.
What They Did
The researchers used two telescope networks—one in South Korea and another called DREAMS (DECam Rogue Earths and Mars Survey)—to watch for a rare cosmic phenomenon. When a star passes precisely in front of another, more distant star, gravity acts like a natural lens, temporarily brightening the background star's light. If the foreground star has a planet, that planet creates a distinctive blip in the brightness pattern. Think of it like watching shadows on a wall—the planet's gravitational "shadow" briefly distorts the light in a telltale way. The DREAMS telescopes took pictures every minute, providing incredibly detailed measurements that helped the team distinguish between different possible explanations for what they observed.
Key Findings
The astronomers discovered a Neptune-sized world about 40 times more massive than Earth, orbiting a small red dwarf star roughly one-third the mass of our Sun. This planetary system sits about 25,000 light-years away in the direction of our galaxy's central bulge. The planet orbits at roughly 1.6 times the Earth-Sun distance—placing it in the outer regions of its solar system, similar to where we'd find asteroids in our own cosmic neighborhood.
Looking Forward
This discovery proves that the DREAMS survey can detect planets as small as Mars floating freely through space without any host star, and even Moon-sized objects in certain regions of our galaxy. This capability could revolutionize our understanding of planetary formation and help answer whether rogue planets—worlds ejected from their birth systems—are common throughout the cosmos.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of disc photoevaporation on the long-term evolution of giant planets in mean motion resonances</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10811v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10811v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:57:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Emmanuel J. Greenfield, James E. Owen</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine two giant planets locked in a cosmic dance, orbiting their star in perfect sync—one completing exactly two orbits for every three of its companion, or three orbits for every four. These "resonant" relationships are surprisingly common among the thousands of exoplanets we've discovered, but scientists have struggled to understand how they form and why some survive while others fall apart. This research tackles a crucial missing piece of the puzzle: how intense starlight strips away the gas disks where planets are born, fundamentally changing their orbital evolution and potentially explaining the diverse planetary systems we observe throughout our galaxy.
What They Did
The researchers created detailed computer simulations of planetary systems during their birth phase, when giant planets are still embedded in swirling disks of gas and dust around young stars. They modeled a process called photoevaporation, where intense ultraviolet radiation from the central star heats up and blows away the surrounding gas—like how a hair dryer can scatter lightweight particles. By running dozens of simulations with different combinations of disk mass, planet size, and resonance types, they tracked how this gas loss affects the delicate gravitational relationships between planet pairs over millions of years.
Key Findings
The team discovered that photoevaporation acts like a cosmic mediator, sometimes saving planetary relationships and sometimes destroying them. When starlight strips away gas from the region between two planets, it can actually stabilize their orbital dance by reducing disruptive gravitational interactions. This effect is strongest for tightly-spaced planet pairs. However, the same process can destabilize other systems by creating uneven gravitational forces. Surprisingly, even when planetary orbits remain stable, photoevaporation typically makes them more elliptical rather than circular.
Looking Forward
These findings could revolutionize our understanding of planetary system architecture throughout the universe. They suggest that the intense radiation environments around young stars play a previously underappreciated role in sculpting the final arrangements of planets. This research will help astronomers interpret observations from missions like Gaia, which precisely measures stellar movements caused by orbiting planets, potentially revealing countless new resonant systems shaped by these ancient processes.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metal Pipe: A Broadly-Applicable Stellar Abundance Pipeline Using Isochronal Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10794v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10794v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:57:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jared R. Kolecki, Lauren M. Weiss</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[# Scientists Develop New Tool to Better Study Stars That Host Other Worlds
Why It Matters
When astronomers discover planets orbiting distant stars, they want to know what those stars are made of—because a star's composition tells us a lot about the planets around it. Think of it like studying a baker to understand their cookies: the ingredients available shape what gets made. But analyzing thousands of different stars consistently has been like trying to use the same recipe in kitchens with completely different equipment. This research tackles that problem by creating a universal tool that can study the chemical makeup of many different types of stars in the same reliable way, helping us better understand the diverse worlds beyond our solar system.
What They Did
The researchers built a new computer program called Metal Pipe that works like a sophisticated chemical analyzer for stars. Just as a food scientist might use consistent methods to analyze the nutritional content of different recipes, this tool takes the rainbow of light from any star (captured by powerful telescopes) and figures out what elements are present and in what amounts. The program combines existing stellar analysis software with carefully selected reference data and a curated list of specific wavelengths of light that reveal different chemical elements. They tested their tool on 503 sun-like stars to make sure it worked accurately across different star types.
Key Findings
Metal Pipe successfully measured ten different elements in stars, including carbon, oxygen, silicon, and iron. When the researchers compared their results to previous measurements of the same stars, they found their tool was remarkably consistent—typically within about 100 degrees when measuring star temperatures (out of thousands of degrees total) and within 10% when measuring chemical abundances. This level of precision matches what scientists expect from measurement uncertainties, proving the tool works as intended.
Looking Forward
This standardized approach means astronomers can now build comprehensive chemical catalogs of planet-hosting stars, revealing patterns about how different stellar environments lead to different types of planetary systems. Future research will extend this tool to analyze cooler, smaller stars that are prime targets for finding potentially habitable worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
