<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 03:41:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>A Cool Earth-sized Planet Candidate Transiting a Tenth Magnitude K-dwarf From K2</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-19870v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-19870v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Venner et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Finding planets like Earth around other stars is one of astronomy's greatest quests—and it's much harder than you might think. Most Earth-like worlds are too small and dim to detect with current technology, like trying to spot a firefly next to a searchlight from miles away. This discovery represents a major breakthrough: astronomers have found what appears to be an Earth-sized planet in the habitable zone around a Sun-like star, and crucially, the star is bright enough that we can study this world in detail with future telescopes.
What They Did
The researchers used NASA's K2 space telescope to monitor the brightness of thousands of stars, watching for tiny dips in light that occur when a planet passes in front of its host star—like a solar eclipse, but much smaller. They focused on a star called HD 137010, similar to our Sun but slightly cooler. During their observations in 2017, they detected a single, 10-hour-long dimming event where the star's brightness dropped by just 0.0225%—an incredibly subtle change that required extraordinary precision to detect. The team then analyzed years of additional data from ground-based telescopes and satellites to confirm this wasn't a false alarm caused by other astronomical phenomena.
Key Findings
The planet candidate, dubbed HD 137010 b, is remarkably Earth-like. It's just 6% larger than Earth and orbits its star roughly once every 355 days (compared to Earth's 365-day year). The planet sits about 88% of Earth's distance from its star and receives about 29% of the sunlight Earth gets—placing it near the outer edge of the "habitable zone" where liquid water could potentially exist on its surface.
Looking Forward
This discovery opens an exciting new chapter in exoplanet science. Because the host star is relatively bright and nearby, future space telescopes like the James Webb Space Telescope could potentially analyze the planet's atmosphere for signs of water vapor, oxygen, or other molecules that might indicate habitability—or even life.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Comprehensive Understanding of Planetary Systems through Population-Level, Large-Scale Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18841v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18841v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Francisco J. Pozuelos et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand all animals on Earth by only knowing where they live, but nothing about their size, diet, or behavior. That's essentially where we stand with planets beyond our solar system. Over 30 years of planet hunting has revealed thousands of these "exoplanets," but we know surprisingly little about what they're actually like. Are they rocky like Earth or gassy like Jupiter? Do they have atmospheres that could support life? These aren't just academic questions—understanding planetary diversity is key to knowing whether Earth-like worlds are common or incredibly rare, and whether we might find life elsewhere in the universe.
What They Did
This research is actually a comprehensive review and roadmap rather than a single study. The authors analyzed the current state of exoplanet research, examining thousands of discovered planets to understand what we know versus what we don't. They compared our detection capabilities—which are excellent at finding planets—with our characterization abilities, which tell us what those planets are actually like. Think of it as the difference between spotting distant ships on the horizon versus being able to determine their size, cargo, and destination.
Key Findings
The results reveal a striking imbalance: while we've discovered over 5,000 exoplanets, we have detailed physical information for only a tiny fraction. Most discovered planets remain "physically ambiguous"—we might know they exist and roughly how big they are, but we can't distinguish between fundamentally different types of worlds. Current cutting-edge telescopes like the James Webb Space Telescope excel at studying individual planets in extraordinary detail, but they're too slow to characterize the hundreds or thousands of planets needed to understand broader patterns.
Looking Forward
The authors argue we need a revolutionary new approach for the 2040s: networks of smaller, specialized telescopes that can rapidly study planetary atmospheres and interiors across large samples. This would transform exoplanet science from a field focused on individual discoveries to one that understands planetary systems as a whole—finally answering whether worlds like Earth are cosmic commonalities or extraordinary exceptions.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for a Peak at ~0.3 in the Eccentricity Distribution of Typical Super-Jovian Exoplanets</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18877v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18877v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Sarah Blunt et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
For decades, astronomers have been discovering planets beyond our solar system, revealing that the universe is teeming with worlds vastly different from our own. Among the most intriguing are "super-Jovian" planets—gas giants that dwarf even Jupiter, our solar system's largest planet. Understanding how these massive worlds move through space tells us the story of planetary systems: were they born in peaceful, orderly nurseries, or did they survive chaotic, violent histories? This research helps us decode those origin stories by examining the stretched-out, oval-shaped orbits that many of these giant planets follow around their stars.
What They Did
The researchers analyzed data from the California Legacy Survey, which tracked hundreds of exoplanets discovered by watching how their gravity makes their host stars wobble slightly. Think of it like watching someone spin around while holding an invisible partner—you can tell something is there by the motion. The team focused on the most massive planets, those three to twenty times heavier than Jupiter, and carefully measured how "stretched out" their orbits are. They used sophisticated statistical methods to account for the fact that some types of planets are easier to detect than others, ensuring their results reflected the true population of these worlds rather than just the ones we happen to spot most easily.
Key Findings
The most striking discovery is that super-Jovian planets have a strong preference for moderately stretched orbits. While planets in perfectly circular orbits have an eccentricity of 0, and highly elongated orbits approach 1, these massive planets cluster around an eccentricity of 0.3. About 92% of their statistical models showed this clear peak, meaning these giants are much more likely to travel in somewhat oval-shaped paths rather than nearly circular ones. This pattern was distinctly different from smaller giant planets, suggesting that the most massive worlds experienced different formation histories.
Looking Forward
This finding points toward dramatic origins for the universe's most massive planets. The moderately stretched orbits suggest these worlds survived violent early histories—perhaps including collisions with other massive objects or gravitational battles between multiple giant planets. As we discover more exoplanets with upcoming space missions, astronomers can test whether this pattern holds true across different types of planetary systems, ultimately helping us understand whether our own solar system's relatively calm arrangement is typical or remarkably peaceful.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
