<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 04:27:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>A Narrowband Technosignature Search Toward the Hycean Candidate K2-18b Using the VLA and MeerKAT</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09553v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09553v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>C. D. Tremblay et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Scientists have discovered thousands of planets orbiting other stars, but finding signs of life—or even intelligent life—remains one of astronomy's greatest challenges. K2-18b, a planet about twice Earth's size located 120 light-years away, has captured attention as a potentially habitable world with a hydrogen-rich atmosphere and possible water vapor. If advanced civilizations exist on such planets, they might be broadcasting radio signals into space, just as humans have been doing for over a century. This study represents humanity's first serious attempt to "listen" for artificial radio transmissions from this promising world, marking a new chapter in our search for cosmic neighbors.
What They Did
Researchers used two of the world's most powerful radio telescope arrays—the Very Large Array in New Mexico and MeerKAT in South Africa—to scan K2-18b for artificial radio signals. Think of it like tuning across a cosmic radio dial, searching for narrow-frequency broadcasts that could only come from technology, not natural sources. They observed the planet system multiple times over several months, covering a complete orbit of K2-18b around its star. The team developed sophisticated computer programs to filter out Earth-based interference from cell towers, satellites, and other human technology, while specifically looking for signals that would move in sync with the planet's motion through space—a telltale sign of an extraterrestrial origin.
Key Findings
The search came up empty—no artificial signals were detected from K2-18b. However, this non-detection is scientifically valuable, allowing researchers to rule out the presence of powerful radio transmitters broadcasting at least 10 trillion watts of power (roughly equivalent to all of Earth's current electrical power generation). Any civilization using radio technology at this level or higher would have been spotted by the telescopes.
Looking Forward
While this study found no evidence of alien technology, it established a crucial methodology for future searches around other potentially habitable worlds. As more Earth-like planets are discovered and our radio telescopes become more sensitive, this systematic approach brings us closer to answering one of humanity's most profound questions: are we alone?]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits on the Post-eclipse Emission Spectrum of HD 80606 b From High-Resolution Spectroscop</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09129v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09129v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Luke Finnerty et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine a planet so close to its star that its surface could melt lead, then so far away it becomes a frozen wasteland—all within the same year. HD 80606 b is one of the most extreme worlds we know, following a wildly stretched orbit that makes it a natural laboratory for understanding how planetary atmospheres respond to dramatic temperature swings. By studying this cosmic oddball, scientists can learn how weather and chemistry work on planets unlike anything in our solar system. This research helps us understand the incredible diversity of worlds beyond Earth and pushes the boundaries of our planet-hunting technology.
What They Did
The researchers used one of the world's most powerful telescopes—the Keck Observatory in Hawaii—to analyze infrared light from HD 80606 b just after it passed behind its star (called a secondary eclipse). They focused on the moment when the planet was closest to its star, experiencing scorching temperatures that could fundamentally alter its atmosphere. Using a technique called high-resolution cross-correlation spectroscopy, they essentially created a chemical fingerprint of the planet's atmosphere by examining how different molecules absorb specific wavelengths of light. Think of it like using a prism to split sunlight into a rainbow, but looking for tiny dark lines that reveal what gases are present in the planet's air.
Key Findings
The team found tentative evidence of the planet's atmosphere, though the signal was relatively weak. Their analysis suggests the presence of methane and carbon monoxide in the planet's atmosphere, which aligns with recent observations from the James Webb Space Telescope. Importantly, they found no evidence of a "thermal inversion"—a phenomenon where upper atmospheric layers become hotter than lower ones, like Earth's ozone layer but more extreme. This finding contradicts some predictions about what should happen when this planet gets blasted by intense stellar radiation during its close approach.
Looking Forward
These results demonstrate both the potential and challenges of studying extreme exoplanets. While the findings align with cutting-edge space telescope observations, they highlight the need for even more sensitive instruments to definitively characterize such distant worlds. Future observations could reveal how planetary atmospheres evolve in real-time under extreme conditions, offering insights that could reshape our understanding of planetary science and guide the search for habitable worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterisation of starspot structure and differential rotation of Kepler-411</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09224v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09224v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Mikko Tuomi, András Haris, Thomas Hackman</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Just like our Sun has dark spots that move across its surface, other stars throughout the galaxy also have these mysterious features. Scientists are fascinated by starspots because they're like windows into a star's magnetic personality—revealing how its magnetic field behaves and changes over time. When these spotted stars happen to host planets, researchers get a unique opportunity to study both the star and its planetary system together. Understanding how stars work is crucial because they power all life as we know it, and their behavior directly affects any planets orbiting around them, including whether those worlds could potentially support life.
What They Did
The research team studied a star called Kepler-411, which is known to have at least two planets orbiting around it. They used data from NASA's Kepler Space Telescope, which watched this star continuously for years, measuring tiny changes in its brightness. Think of it like having a super-sensitive light meter pointed at the star 24/7. The scientists used two clever detective methods: first, they tracked how the star's brightness flickered as dark spots rotated in and out of view, like watching shadows move across a spinning ball. Second, they looked for brief dimming events when the star's planets passed in front of spots during their regular orbits—essentially using the planets as scanning devices to map where spots were located on the star's surface.
Key Findings
The team discovered that Kepler-411 rotates like a rigid spinning top, completing one full rotation every 10.52 days (compared to our Sun's 25-day rotation period). Surprisingly, they found no evidence that different parts of the star rotate at different speeds, which is common in stars like our Sun. They successfully caught three instances where one of the planets, called planet c, passed directly over starspots, causing tiny but measurable dips in brightness. These spot locations matched perfectly with their computer models, confirming their mapping technique works.
Looking Forward
This research demonstrates powerful new ways to study distant stars and their planets simultaneously. By understanding how starspots behave, scientists can better predict how stellar activity might affect planetary atmospheres and climates—crucial information for assessing whether exoplanets could harbor life.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Y Dwarf Population with HST: unlocking the secrets of our coolest neighbours -- III. Near-Infrared Photometry</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09160v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-09160v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Clémence Fontanive et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand distant worlds by studying the coldest, faintest objects in our cosmic neighborhood. Y dwarfs are "failed stars"—objects too small to ignite nuclear fusion—with surface temperatures cooler than your kitchen oven. These dim brown dwarfs are cosmic laboratories that help us understand giant planets orbiting other stars, since they share similar temperatures and atmospheric conditions. By studying these nearby examples in detail, astronomers can better interpret the faint signals we detect from actual exoplanets billions of miles away. It's like having a reference library of planetary atmospheres right in our galactic backyard.
What They Did
The research team used the Hubble Space Telescope to take extremely precise photographs of 21 Y dwarfs through different infrared filters—essentially cosmic color filters that reveal how bright these objects appear in specific wavelengths of light invisible to human eyes. Think of it like photographing the same object through red, green, and blue filters to understand its true colors. They developed sophisticated techniques to measure the brightness of these incredibly faint objects with remarkable precision, achieving accuracy levels comparable to distinguishing between a 100-watt and 102-watt lightbulb from across a football field. They also used precise distance measurements to create detailed charts showing how these objects' colors and brightness relate to their temperatures.
Key Findings
The team discovered that Y dwarfs follow surprisingly predictable patterns when organized by temperature and color, forming tight sequences on astronomical charts with far less scatter than previously observed. However, when they compared their measurements to theoretical models—computer simulations that predict how these objects should appear—they found systematic mismatches. The models consistently predicted colors that were too red compared to reality, suggesting our understanding of atmospheric physics at these extreme cold temperatures remains incomplete.
Looking Forward
These precise measurements provide a crucial reality check for atmospheric models used to interpret exoplanet observations. As next-generation telescopes prepare to study Earth-like worlds around other stars, having accurate models becomes essential for determining which planets might harbor conditions suitable for life.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
