<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of four cold Jupiters through combined analyses of radial velocity and astrometry data</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11280v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11280v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Yiyun Wu et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand how our solar system formed by only studying Earth and Mars—you'd miss the crucial role that Jupiter played in shaping everything around it. That's exactly the challenge astronomers face when studying distant planetary systems. Jupiter-like planets that orbit far from their stars, called "cold Jupiters," are cosmic architects that influence how entire planetary systems develop. Yet these distant giants are notoriously difficult to spot and study. This research tackles that challenge head-on, uncovering four new cold Jupiters and demonstrating a powerful new method for finding many more. Understanding these distant worlds helps us piece together the story of how planetary systems—including our own—came to be.
What They Did
The researchers combined two detective techniques to hunt for these elusive planets. First, they used radial velocity measurements, which detect the tiny wobble a planet causes as it tugs on its host star—like watching a dog walker get pulled back and forth by an invisible leash. Second, they incorporated data from the Gaia space telescope, which precisely tracks how stars move across the sky over decades. When a star has a hidden planetary companion, its motion becomes slightly erratic, like a person walking while carrying an invisible, shifting weight. By combining these two approaches over a 25-year period, the team could determine not just that planets exist, but their exact masses, orbital tilts, and three-dimensional paths through space.
Key Findings
The team discovered four cold Jupiters, each taking years to decades to complete a single orbit around their stars. The most extreme, dubbed HD 68475 b, takes over 21 years to circle its star and weighs about five times more than Jupiter. Another standout is HD 100508 b, which completes its 15-year orbit while weighing slightly more than Jupiter. Two others were found in multi-planet systems, including one that may be tilted dramatically compared to its planetary neighbor—a configuration that could reveal how planetary systems can become dynamically unstable over time. Remarkably, one of these worlds holds the record for the longest orbital period among planets in its mass range.
Looking Forward
This research opens a new chapter in exoplanet discovery. The success of combining stellar wobbles with precise positional measurements suggests that thousands more cold Jupiters are waiting to be found in existing Gaia data. Some of these newly discovered worlds, particularly HD 68475 b, are prime candidates for direct imaging with next-generation telescopes, potentially allowing astronomers to study their atmospheres and compositions directly. As more cold Jupiters are uncovered, scientists will finally have the large sample sizes needed to solve long-standing mysteries about how these cosmic architects form and sculpt planetary systems across the galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aligned, Misaligned and Polar Orbits of Hot Jupiters: Measuring Spin-Orbit Angles via Doppler Tomography with HARPS-N</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11313v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11313v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Z. Balkóová et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine throwing a baseball perfectly straight while spinning like a top—that's how we'd expect planets to orbit their stars, moving in the same direction as the star's rotation. But the universe loves to surprise us. Scientists have discovered that many "hot Jupiters"—massive planets that orbit incredibly close to their stars—move in bizarre ways: some travel backward, others loop around their star's poles like a Ferris wheel. These strange orbits hold crucial clues about how planetary systems form and evolve, helping us understand whether our own solar system's neat, orderly arrangement is common or remarkably special.
What They Did
The researchers used a clever technique called Doppler tomography to study three hot Jupiter planets. When a planet passes in front of its star (like a tiny eclipse), it blocks different parts of the star's spinning surface. Since one side of a spinning star moves toward us and the other moves away, this creates a distinctive signature in the star's light—like a shadow moving across the star's face. By carefully analyzing this shadow using three different computer programs and a sensitive instrument called HARPS-N, the scientists could determine exactly how each planet's orbit is tilted compared to its star's rotation. Think of it like figuring out whether a marble rolling around a spinning basketball follows the equator, goes over the poles, or takes some other crazy path.
Key Findings
The three planets showed dramatically different behaviors. HAT-P-57A b is the "well-behaved" one, orbiting almost perfectly aligned with its star's equator. XO-3A b is moderately tilted at 38 degrees—imagine a planet taking a diagonal path around its star. Most remarkably, HAT-P-49 b is nearly polar, orbiting at 85 degrees—essentially going over its star's north and south poles rather than around its equator. This polar orbit is like a planet doing loop-the-loops instead of following a normal circular track.
Looking Forward
These findings add to growing evidence that planetary systems can be far more chaotic than our own solar system suggests. Understanding why some hot Jupiters end up in such extreme orbits helps scientists piece together the violent early histories of planetary systems—including whether planets migrate inward through gentle gravitational interactions or dramatic collisions and ejections. This research brings us closer to answering fundamental questions about how common Earth-like, stable planetary systems truly are in our galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metal Pipe: A Broadly-Applicable Stellar Abundance Pipeline Using Isochronal Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10794v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10794v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jared R. Kolecki, Lauren M. Weiss</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[# Scientists Develop New Tool to Better Study Stars That Host Other Worlds
Why It Matters
When astronomers discover planets orbiting distant stars, they want to know what those stars are made of—because a star's composition tells us a lot about the planets around it. Think of it like studying a baker to understand their cookies: the ingredients available shape what gets made. But analyzing thousands of different stars consistently has been like trying to use the same recipe in kitchens with completely different equipment. This research tackles that problem by creating a universal tool that can study the chemical makeup of many different types of stars in the same reliable way, helping us better understand the diverse worlds beyond our solar system.
What They Did
The researchers built a new computer program called Metal Pipe that works like a sophisticated chemical analyzer for stars. Just as a food scientist might use consistent methods to analyze the nutritional content of different recipes, this tool takes the rainbow of light from any star (captured by powerful telescopes) and figures out what elements are present and in what amounts. The program combines existing stellar analysis software with carefully selected reference data and a curated list of specific wavelengths of light that reveal different chemical elements. They tested their tool on 503 sun-like stars to make sure it worked accurately across different star types.
Key Findings
Metal Pipe successfully measured ten different elements in stars, including carbon, oxygen, silicon, and iron. When the researchers compared their results to previous measurements of the same stars, they found their tool was remarkably consistent—typically within about 100 degrees when measuring star temperatures (out of thousands of degrees total) and within 10% when measuring chemical abundances. This level of precision matches what scientists expect from measurement uncertainties, proving the tool works as intended.
Looking Forward
This standardized approach means astronomers can now build comprehensive chemical catalogs of planet-hosting stars, revealing patterns about how different stellar environments lead to different types of planetary systems. Future research will extend this tool to analyze cooler, smaller stars that are prime targets for finding potentially habitable worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KMT-2025-BLG-1616Lb: First Microlensing Bound Planet From DREAMS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11469v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11469v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Hongjing Yang et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to spot a firefly buzzing around a lighthouse from thousands of miles away—that's essentially the challenge astronomers face when hunting for planets orbiting distant stars. This research represents a breakthrough in our ability to find these elusive worlds using a technique called gravitational microlensing, which acts like a natural magnifying glass in space. What makes this discovery particularly exciting is that it demonstrates how new technology can reveal planets we could never detect before, including potentially "rogue" planets drifting alone through the galaxy without any star to call home.
What They Did
The researchers used two telescope networks—one in Korea and another called DREAMS—to monitor millions of stars simultaneously, watching for a telltale brightening that occurs when a closer star (and any planets around it) passes directly in front of a more distant star. Think of it like watching someone walk in front of a streetlight: the person's gravity acts as a lens, bending and focusing the light to make it appear brighter. The Korean telescopes spotted the initial signal, but DREAMS's rapid-fire observations—taking pictures every minute—provided the crucial detail needed to confirm that a planet was responsible for a subtle blip in the brightness pattern.
Key Findings
The team discovered a Neptune-sized planet about 40 times more massive than Earth, orbiting a small red dwarf star roughly 25,000 light-years away toward the center of our galaxy. The planet sits about 1.6 times farther from its star than Earth does from the Sun—roughly the distance of Mars from our Sun. The host star itself is quite modest, weighing only about one-third as much as our Sun.
Looking Forward
This success proves that DREAMS can detect incredibly small planets, potentially down to the mass of Mars around distant stars, and even Moon-sized rogue planets wandering the galaxy alone. This opens an entirely new window for discovering the smallest worlds in our cosmic neighborhood and understanding how common planetary systems really are.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of disc photoevaporation on the long-term evolution of giant planets in mean motion resonances</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10811v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10811v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Emmanuel J. Greenfield, James E. Owen</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
When planets form around distant stars, they don't always stay where they started. Like dancers moving to cosmic music, planets can migrate inward toward their host stars and sometimes get locked into synchronized orbits called "resonances"—where one planet completes exactly two or three orbits for every orbit of its neighbor. Understanding what makes these planetary partnerships stable or causes them to fall apart helps us explain why planetary systems look so different from each other, and why our own solar system might be unusual. This research tackles a crucial missing piece: how the gradual evaporation of planet-forming discs affects these delicate orbital relationships.
What They Did
The researchers created detailed computer simulations to watch how pairs of giant planets behave as the gas disc around their star slowly disappears. Think of it like studying how ice dancers perform as the rink gradually melts beneath them. They used a sophisticated program called FARGO3D to model the physics of gas swirling around stars, adding in the effects of high-energy radiation that gradually strips away the disc material—a process called photoevaporation. The team tested different scenarios by varying the disc's mass, how thick or thin the gas was, the sizes of the planets, and the types of orbital resonances to see what happened in each case.
Key Findings
The results revealed surprising complexity. Strong photoevaporation actually helps stabilize the more fragile 3:2 resonances (where the inner planet completes three orbits for every two of the outer planet) by removing gas between the planets and reducing disruptive forces. However, the more naturally stable 2:1 resonances can paradoxically become unstable under certain conditions when photoevaporation creates uneven gravitational tugs. In nearly all cases, planets ended up on more stretched-out, oval-shaped orbits rather than circular ones.
Looking Forward
These findings suggest that planetary system architecture depends heavily on how and when the birth disc disappears—meaning identical starting conditions can produce dramatically different outcomes. This helps explain the incredible diversity of exoplanetary systems we observe and provides crucial context for upcoming space missions like Gaia, which will measure the subtle wobbles of nearby stars caused by orbiting planets.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central flashes during stellar occultations. Effects of diffraction, interferences, and stellar diameter</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11380v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-11380v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Sicardy, Luc Dettwiller</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
When distant worlds pass in front of stars, they create cosmic shadow shows that reveal secrets about their atmospheres. These events, called stellar occultations, are like natural laboratories that let astronomers study planets and moons throughout our solar system—and potentially beyond. But there's a surprising twist: sometimes these shadows aren't completely dark. Instead, they can produce brilliant flashes of light right at their centers, creating what scientists call "central flashes." Understanding these flashes is crucial because they contain detailed information about atmospheric conditions on distant worlds, helping us learn about places we may never visit in person.
What They Did
The researchers created detailed mathematical models to understand exactly how these mysterious flashes form. Think of it like figuring out why you sometimes see bright spots in shadows cast by curved glass—the physics is similar but much more complex. They examined how starlight bends and interferes when it passes through the thin atmospheres of distant objects like Pluto and Neptune's moon Triton. The team considered various factors: whether the star appears as a single point of light or has measurable width, how thick the atmosphere is, and how light waves interact with each other after passing through the atmospheric "lens."
Key Findings
The research revealed that these central flashes can be incredibly intense—potentially 10,000 to 100,000 times brighter than normal in ideal conditions, though usually reduced to more modest levels of 50 to 200 times brighter in real observations. The flashes are remarkably tiny, appearing in regions just meters wide on Earth despite originating from events millions of miles away. Denser atmospheres create more focused, intense flashes, while thinner atmospheres produce broader, dimmer ones. The exact shape and brightness depend on the size of the star and the wavelength of light being observed.
Looking Forward
These findings could revolutionize how we study not just objects in our solar system, but potentially exoplanets orbiting other stars. By precisely understanding central flashes, astronomers can extract far more detailed information about atmospheric composition, density, and structure from occultation events, turning these cosmic alignments into powerful tools for exploring distant worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotation Period of 3I/ATLAS After Perihelion from Jet Position Angle Wobble and Photometric Variability</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10860v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-10860v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Toni Scarmato, Abraham Loeb</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
When mysterious visitors from other star systems zip through our solar neighborhood, scientists race to learn everything they can before they disappear forever. The object 3I/ATLAS is only the third known interstellar visitor we've detected—a cosmic wanderer that originated somewhere beyond our Sun's influence and is now heading back to deep space. Understanding how fast these objects spin and how they behave gives us rare glimpses into the conditions around distant stars, potentially revealing clues about how planetary systems form and evolve throughout the galaxy. It's like having an alien postcard delivered directly to our doorstep.
What They Did
Researchers used two clever detective methods to figure out how fast 3I/ATLAS spins. First, they tracked a jet of gas and dust shooting out from the object using the Hubble Space Telescope, watching how this jet wobbled back and forth like a spinning garden sprinkler. They photographed the object repeatedly over more than a month and measured how the jet's direction changed over time. Second, they used a ground-based telescope to monitor how bright the object appeared, looking for regular dimming and brightening patterns—similar to how a lighthouse beam appears to pulse as it rotates. They then used mathematical techniques to find repeating patterns in both the jet wobbling and brightness changes.
Key Findings
The two methods revealed that 3I/ATLAS completes one full rotation in approximately 7.1 hours—about four times faster than Earth's 24-hour day. The jet measurement suggested 7.2 hours, while the brightness variations indicated 7.136 hours. This slight difference likely comes from measurement uncertainties rather than representing two different phenomena. The researchers also discovered that the jet doesn't shoot straight out from the object's north or south pole, but instead sweeps around in a cone-like pattern, tilted about 20 degrees from the rotation axis.
Looking Forward
While this research focuses on an interstellar object rather than an exoplanet, the techniques developed here advance our ability to study distant spinning bodies throughout the universe. These methods could help astronomers better understand how planets and asteroids rotate in other star systems, providing crucial data for determining whether distant worlds might be habitable or how planetary systems evolve over billions of years.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
