<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 03:53:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>TOI-6692b: An eccentric 130 day period giant planet with a single transit from TESS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16357v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16357v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Allyson Bieryla et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to solve a jigsaw puzzle with only one piece visible for a brief moment every four months. That's essentially what astronomers faced when they spotted a single, mysterious signal from a distant world called TOI-6692b. This discovery matters because it showcases how modern astronomy can piece together the story of an entire planet from just fleeting glimpses. Finding planets with such long orbital periods—those that take months to complete one "year"—helps us understand how planetary systems like our own solar system form and evolve over billions of years.
What They Did
The planet was first spotted by citizen scientists volunteers who comb through data from TESS, NASA's planet-hunting telescope. They noticed a single dimming event as the planet passed in front of its star—like watching a moth briefly cross a distant streetlight. To confirm this wasn't just a fluke, astronomers used multiple ground-based telescopes around the world to measure tiny wobbles in the star caused by the planet's gravitational pull. They also attempted to catch the planet crossing its star again by timing their observations to coincide with when they predicted the next transit would occur, despite having only one previous sighting to work with.
Key Findings
TOI-6692b is a gas giant similar to Jupiter but follows a highly stretched-out, oval-shaped orbit that takes 130 days to complete. Its path is so eccentric that it swings much closer and farther from its star during each orbit—imagine Earth having summers hot enough to melt lead and winters colder than Mars. The planet's 11-hour-long transit makes it one of the few distant worlds where astronomers have nailed down its mass, size, and orbital shape with confidence.
Looking Forward
This discovery demonstrates that even single, brief observations can unlock planetary secrets when combined with persistent follow-up work. The techniques used here will help astronomers find more distant worlds and better understand how planets get kicked into such extreme orbits.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mercury-Arχes: a high-performance n-body code for planet formation studies</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16791v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16791v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Diego Turrini et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand how a bustling city develops by watching it in fast-forward over centuries—that's essentially what scientists are doing when they study how planets form around distant stars. This research matters because it helps us answer one of humanity's most profound questions: How common are planetary systems like our own? By creating more powerful computer simulations of planet formation, researchers can better predict what kinds of worlds exist beyond our solar system and whether Earth-like planets capable of supporting life are rare cosmic accidents or common occurrences throughout the galaxy.
What They Did
The researchers developed a sophisticated computer program called Mercury-Arχes that acts like a cosmic flight simulator for planet formation. Just as flight simulators must track thousands of variables simultaneously—weather, physics, mechanical systems—this program tracks the gravitational dance between countless objects in a young solar system: massive gas giant planets, rocky worlds like Earth, and swarms of smaller bodies like asteroids and comets. The challenge is that these simulations must also account for the swirling disk of gas that surrounds young stars, which pushes and pulls on forming planets like a cosmic wind. To handle these incredibly complex calculations, the team optimized their program to run on multiple computer processors simultaneously, like having dozens of calculators working together on the same massive equation.
Key Findings
The main achievement is a dramatically more efficient simulation tool that can model planet formation with unprecedented detail and speed. By using parallel processing techniques, the program can simultaneously track the interactions between thousands of planetary bodies while accounting for gas disk effects—something that would have taken prohibitively long with older methods.
Looking Forward
This computational breakthrough will allow scientists to run more comprehensive simulations of how different types of planetary systems form, helping us understand why some stars host multiple Earth-sized worlds while others have only gas giants. These insights will prove invaluable as next-generation telescopes discover thousands of new exoplanets.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Origins of Planets for ArieL (OPAL) Key Science Project: the end-to-end planet formation campaign for the ESA space mission Ariel</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16841v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16841v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Danae Polychroni et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine if every person on Earth had wildly different air to breathe—some with oxygen-rich atmospheres, others thick with methane, and still others as thin as mountaintop air. This is exactly what scientists are discovering about planets beyond our solar system. Thousands of exoplanets have been found, and they show an incredible diversity not just in size and temperature, but in the very air that surrounds them. Understanding why these planetary atmospheres are so different could unlock the secrets of how planets form and whether any might harbor life. It's like having a cosmic detective story where the atmosphere holds the clues to each planet's origin story.
What They Did
To prepare for Ariel, an upcoming European space telescope that will study hundreds of exoplanet atmospheres, researchers created something like a massive recipe book for planetary atmospheres. They built computer simulations that follow the entire "life story" of a planet—starting from the swirling disk of gas and dust around a young star, through the planet's formation, and ending with its final atmospheric composition. Think of it as creating a family tree that connects each planet to its birthplace. Their simulations track dozens of chemical elements and hundreds of different molecules, creating a library of realistic artificial atmospheres that spans the full range of possibilities scientists expect to find in space.
Key Findings
The research revealed that even tiny differences in starting conditions can lead to dramatically different planetary outcomes. Like how small changes in a recipe can completely alter the final dish, minor variations in the original disk of material around a star can produce planets with vastly different atmospheric compositions. This helps explain the stunning diversity scientists observe in real exoplanets and shows that the universe is capable of creating an almost endless variety of worlds.
Looking Forward
This work provides the essential groundwork for interpreting future discoveries from the Ariel mission. When the telescope begins observing real exoplanets, scientists will have this comprehensive library to compare against, helping them decode what each atmosphere reveals about its planet's formation history and potential for supporting life.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>proto-Lightspeed: a high-speed, ultra-low read noise imager on the Magellan Clay Telescope</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16268v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16268v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Layden et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to photograph a firefly blinking on and off in your backyard while standing a mile away. That's essentially what astronomers face when studying rapidly changing events in space—like planets passing in front of distant stars, or explosive flares from cosmic objects. These fleeting celestial events happen incredibly fast and are extremely faint, making them nearly impossible to capture with traditional telescopes. Missing these brief moments means losing crucial clues about how planets form, how stars behave, and what strange objects lurk in the outer reaches of our solar system. This is why astronomers desperately needed a new kind of cosmic camera.
What They Did
Scientists built an ultra-fast space camera called proto-Lightspeed and attached it to one of the world's most powerful telescopes in Chile. Think of it as upgrading from an old film camera to the most advanced high-speed digital camera imaginable. This new instrument can take up to 200 pictures per second of the entire viewing area, or an incredible 6,600 pictures per second when focused on smaller regions of sky. The camera is so sensitive it can detect almost individual particles of light, with virtually no background noise that typically ruins faint astronomical images. The team used commercially available lenses combined with cutting-edge Japanese camera technology, proving that sometimes the best scientific tools come from clever combinations of existing technology.
Key Findings
The camera successfully captured razor-sharp images during its test runs, proving it can spot the kinds of rapid changes astronomers have been trying to study for years. It can photograph objects across different colors of light simultaneously and adjust its magnification like a zoom lens. The instrument works so well that it will become available to the international astronomy community in 2026, giving researchers worldwide access to this powerful new tool.
Looking Forward
This technology opens entirely new windows into the universe's most dynamic events. Astronomers will finally be able to study how planets affect their host stars during transits, catch mysterious objects in the outer solar system as they briefly block background starlight, and witness the split-second flares that reveal secrets about cosmic collisions and explosions. The team is already planning an even more advanced version that could revolutionize how we discover and study exoplanets.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
