<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 04:22:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Analysis for Remote Biosignature Identification on exoEarths (BARBIE) IV: Analyzing CO2 Detections in the Near-IR to Determine the Long-Wavelength Cut-off for the Habitable Worlds Observatory Coronagraph</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12353v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12353v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Celeste Hagee et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to determine if a distant house has people living in it by analyzing the light coming through its windows. That's essentially what astronomers are attempting with planets orbiting other stars—searching for signs of life by studying the gases in their atmospheres. Carbon dioxide is one of the most important clues we can look for, as it tells us about a planet's climate, geology, and potentially its ability to support life. This research is crucial because NASA is planning to build the Habitable Worlds Observatory, a revolutionary space telescope designed to hunt for Earth-like worlds. Getting the telescope's design right the first time is essential, since this billion-dollar instrument will be our best shot at finding life beyond our solar system.
What They Did
The researchers used computer simulations to test how well we could detect carbon dioxide in the atmospheres of Earth-like planets around other stars. They created virtual observations using different telescope settings, much like a photographer testing various camera filters to get the best shot. Specifically, they tested 25 different "filters" that would capture light at wavelengths between 0.8 and 2.0 micrometers—a range that includes near-infrared light just beyond what our eyes can see. They simulated planets with different amounts of carbon dioxide, from levels found on ancient Earth to those on Venus today, and calculated how clear the detection signals would be under various conditions.
Key Findings
The team discovered that the telescope should focus on light up to 1.68 micrometers for optimal carbon dioxide detection—this specific wavelength range provides the best balance of signal strength and clarity. They found that other gases significantly affect carbon dioxide detection: methane and water vapor can either help or hinder the process, while carbon monoxide proved nearly impossible to detect reliably regardless of its abundance levels.
Looking Forward
These findings will directly influence the design of humanity's next great planet-hunting telescope. By knowing exactly which wavelengths of light to prioritize, engineers can optimize the observatory's instruments for the best chance of detecting potentially habitable worlds and signs of life beyond Earth.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TIC-65910228 b / NGTS-38 b, a 180 day transiting warm super-Jupiter</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12977v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12977v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Toby Rodel et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Most planets we've discovered orbiting other stars fall into two categories: scorching hot worlds that race around their stars in days, or distant, cold planets that take years to complete an orbit. But there's a fascinating middle ground—warm planets with moderate orbital periods—that could teach us crucial lessons about how planetary systems form and evolve. These "warm Jupiters" might represent a missing link in our understanding of planetary migration, helping explain how giant planets end up in such diverse configurations throughout the galaxy.
What They Did
This discovery began when NASA's planet-hunting telescope TESS spotted a single, mysterious dip in starlight—the signature of a planet crossing in front of its star. But with only one transit observed, astronomers faced a puzzle: when would this planet pass by again? The research team launched an ambitious monitoring campaign using ground-based telescopes, essentially playing cosmic detective. They watched the target star for 228 nights using the Next-Generation Transit Survey, while simultaneously measuring tiny wobbles in the star's motion using specialized instruments that can detect movement as small as a person walking on a distant mountaintop.
Key Findings
The planet, designated NGTS-38 b, is truly remarkable. It's a "super-Jupiter"—nearly five times more massive than Jupiter but only slightly larger, making it incredibly dense. The planet takes 180 days to orbit its star (compared to Jupiter's 12 years), placing it in the rare category of warm Jupiters. Its orbit is noticeably oval-shaped rather than circular, and the planet experiences temperatures around 185°C (365°F)—hot enough to melt lead, but relatively cool by exoplanet standards. The host star is metal-rich and bright enough to study in detail from Earth.
Looking Forward
NGTS-38 b represents a crucial piece in the planetary formation puzzle. Its unique properties make it an excellent target for future studies that could reveal whether it has moons, rings, or unusual atmospheric compositions. The upcoming PLATO space mission will monitor this system continuously, potentially discovering additional planets and refining our understanding of this intriguing world.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Protoplanet Candidate in the PDS 66 Disk Indicated by Silicon Sulfide Isotopologues</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12522v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12522v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Tomohiro C. Yoshida et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Scientists have long wondered how tiny space pebbles grow into massive planets like Jupiter or Earth. While we can observe the building blocks of planets—dust and gas swirling around young stars—catching planets in the act of forming has proven incredibly difficult. It's like trying to photograph a child growing up by taking just one snapshot. This research represents a potential breakthrough: astronomers may have found chemical fingerprints of a planet still under construction, giving us a rare glimpse into one of the universe's most fundamental processes.
What They Did
The research team used the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array, a collection of radio telescopes in Chile that can detect molecules in space by their unique chemical signatures. They pointed these telescopes at PDS 66, a young star system located about 370 light-years away, and searched for specific molecules containing silicon and sulfur. Think of it like using a very sensitive nose to detect the aroma of baking bread wafting from a kitchen—except they were "smelling" molecules around a distant star to understand what's happening there.
Key Findings
The team detected silicon sulfide molecules in a surprisingly small, hot region about 60 times farther from the star than Earth is from our Sun. What makes this discovery remarkable is the sheer quantity: they found enough silicon to account for at least 10% of all the silicon normally locked up in dust grains in that area. Since dust grains don't typically release this much silicon unless something dramatic happens, the researchers believe they're seeing evidence of a forming planet. This protoplanet would be gobbling up space pebbles and heating them so intensely that they vaporize, releasing their silicon into the surrounding gas.
Looking Forward
This detection opens a new window into planet formation. If confirmed, it demonstrates that we can use molecular chemistry as a tool to find planets still in their cosmic cribs. Future observations could reveal how common this process is and help astronomers understand whether our own solar system formed through similar mechanisms billions of years ago.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TSSC comet-centered data products from TESS 3I/ATLAS observations</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12364v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12364v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Martinez-Palomera, Amy Tuson, TESS Science Support Center</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine a cosmic visitor from another star system racing through our solar neighborhood—that's exactly what happened with 3I/ATLAS, only the third interstellar object ever discovered passing through our Solar System. These rare cosmic wanderers offer scientists an extraordinary opportunity to study material that formed around distant stars billions of years ago. Unlike asteroids and comets born in our own solar system, interstellar objects carry secrets from alien worlds, potentially revealing how other planetary systems formed and evolved. By studying 3I/ATLAS, we're essentially getting a free sample delivery from deep space—no expensive interstellar mission required.
What They Did
NASA's planet-hunting telescope TESS (Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite) turned its powerful eye toward this interstellar visitor during a week-long observation campaign in January 2026. Think of TESS as a cosmic photographer taking pictures every 20 to 200 seconds—incredibly fast for space observations. The research team created two specialized data sets: first, a series of images that track the comet's movement across the sky while filtering out interfering starlight and background noise, and second, measurements of how bright the comet appeared over time. They've made these processed observations freely available to scientists worldwide, essentially creating a detailed photo album and brightness diary of this rare visitor.
Key Findings
This paper primarily presents the observational data rather than scientific discoveries, but the achievement itself is remarkable. TESS captured unprecedented high-precision, nearly continuous observations of 3I/ATLAS just after its closest approach to our Sun—the most active period in any comet's journey when solar heating causes dramatic changes in brightness and activity.
Looking Forward
While TESS specializes in finding exoplanets, this research demonstrates how planet-hunting tools can unlock secrets about interstellar visitors. These detailed observations will help scientists understand how comets from other star systems behave, potentially revealing differences from our local comets and providing clues about the conditions around distant stars where planets might form.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TIC65910228b: A single-transit discovery of a massive long-period warm Jupiter with TESS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-13125v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-13125v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Felipe I. Rojas et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand how our solar system formed by studying only Earth and Mars. That's essentially the challenge astronomers face when studying giant planets like Jupiter. Most exoplanets we've discovered orbit extremely close to their stars, completing their "years" in just days or weeks. But these scorching hot worlds tell us little about planets like Jupiter, which takes 12 Earth years to complete one orbit. This new discovery helps fill a crucial gap in our understanding of how giant planets form and evolve, particularly those that orbit at moderate distances from their stars—close enough to be warm, but not so close that they're roasted.
What They Did
The team started with a single snapshot of a planet crossing in front of its star, captured by NASA's planet-hunting TESS telescope. Think of it like seeing someone walk past a streetlight just once—you know something passed by, but you need more information to figure out what it was. The researchers then used ground-based telescopes around the world to gather additional clues. They measured how the star wobbled due to the planet's gravitational pull (like a dog walker being tugged by their pet) and watched for additional transits to nail down the planet's orbital period. By combining these different types of observations, they could determine the planet's size, mass, and orbital characteristics.
Key Findings
Meet TIC65910228b: a behemoth planet that weighs four and a half times more than Jupiter but is surprisingly compact—only slightly larger than Jupiter in size. This makes it incredibly dense, like a bowling ball compared to a basketball. The planet orbits its star every 180 days (roughly six Earth months) in an oval-shaped path, coming closer and farther from its star during each orbit. It circles an evolved star similar to our Sun but older and slightly more massive.
Looking Forward
This discovery demonstrates that single transit detections—previously considered too uncertain to pursue—can yield significant scientific discoveries. As more of these "one-shot" planets are confirmed, astronomers will build a better census of long-period giant planets, helping us understand whether our solar system's architecture is common or unusual in the cosmic neighborhood.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GAMERA-OP: A three-dimensional finite-volume MHD solver for orthogonal curvilinear geometries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12307v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12307v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Hongyang Luo et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand how planets form around distant stars, or how the magnetic fields around these worlds behave—it's like trying to predict weather patterns in a hurricane while sitting thousands of miles away. Scientists studying exoplanets (planets orbiting other stars) face exactly this challenge. They need powerful computer simulations to model the complex magnetic and fluid dynamics happening around these distant worlds. This research introduces a new computational tool that could revolutionize how we study the magnetic environments of exoplanets, potentially helping us understand which worlds might be habitable.
What They Did
The researchers built a sophisticated computer program called GAMERA-OP—think of it as a virtual laboratory for studying plasma (super-hot, electrically charged gas) in space. Just as video games need powerful graphics engines to render realistic 3D worlds, scientists need specialized software to simulate the invisible magnetic fields and swirling gases around planets and stars. Their program is like upgrading from basic 2D drawings to high-definition 3D movies. It can handle curved coordinate systems (imagine mapping weather on a sphere rather than a flat surface) and maintains mathematical precision that previous tools struggled with. The team rewrote the entire program in a more efficient computer language and designed it like LEGO blocks—modular pieces that can be easily combined or modified for different research questions.
Key Findings
The new tool passed all standard accuracy tests while using significantly less computational power than previous methods. It maintains perfect mathematical precision for magnetic field calculations—something that sounds technical but is crucial for realistic simulations. The program excels at handling rotating systems and complex geometries, making it particularly valuable for studying spinning planets and their magnetic fields.
Looking Forward
This advancement could accelerate discoveries about exoplanet atmospheres and magnetic shields—factors that determine whether distant worlds could potentially support life. Better simulations mean better predictions about which exoplanets deserve closer study with future space telescopes.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrophysics Wrapped 2025: Year-in-Review of Every Astrophysics arXiv Paper from 2025</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12303v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12303v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rommulus Francis Lewis, Hetansh Shah, Amruth Alfred</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to keep up with every conversation happening at a massive scientific conference with thousands of researchers all talking at once. That's essentially what's happening in astronomy today—so many discoveries are being made that even professional astronomers struggle to stay informed about breakthroughs outside their specialty. This research tackles that overwhelming flood of information by creating the ultimate "year in review" for space science, analyzing every single astronomy paper published in 2025. For anyone curious about where we stand in our quest to understand the universe, this study reveals which cosmic mysteries are capturing scientists' attention most and how our knowledge is expanding.
What They Did
The researchers acted like cosmic librarians, systematically cataloging and analyzing thousands of astronomy research papers from 2025. Instead of reading every paper word-for-word—which would take lifetimes—they examined the "metadata," or basic information about each study: how many pages long they were, which keywords appeared most frequently, what telescopes were used, and which cosmic objects were studied most. They also tracked where the researchers worked around the globe and how often their papers were cited by other scientists, creating a comprehensive snapshot of the entire field's activity over one year.
Key Findings
The study revealed fascinating patterns in modern astronomy research. Certain "hot topics" dominated the field, with exoplanets, gravitational waves, gamma-ray bursts, and fast radio bursts capturing significant attention. The research mapped out which telescopes were workhorses of discovery and identified the most-studied cosmic objects. They also uncovered the global nature of modern astronomy, showing how researchers from different continents collaborate and which institutions are leading various types of research.
Looking Forward
This bird's-eye view of astronomy helps both students and seasoned researchers navigate the field more strategically. For exoplanet science specifically, understanding these broader trends means researchers can identify emerging techniques, popular targets for study, and collaboration opportunities that might accelerate the discovery of potentially habitable worlds beyond our solar system.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
