<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 04:30:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>A New Strategy for Using Spectroscopic Phase Curves to Characterize Non-Transiting Planets</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-07127v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-07127v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Ted M. Johnson, Avi M. Mandell</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to study a firefly's glow while it circles a blazing campfire—that's essentially the challenge astronomers face when studying planets orbiting other stars. Most of what we know about exoplanets comes from watching them pass in front of their host stars, like tiny shadows blocking starlight. But the vast majority of planets never cross our line of sight this way, leaving them largely mysterious. This research introduces a clever new method that could unlock the secrets of thousands of previously unstudable worlds, including some that might be suitable for life.
What They Did
The researchers developed a technique they call VPIE (Variable Planetary Infrared Excess) that works like a cosmic game of "spot the difference." As a planet orbits its star, we see different amounts of heat radiating from its day and night sides—sometimes we see the hot day side, sometimes the cooler night side. This creates a subtle flickering pattern in the combined light from the star-planet system. The VPIE method uses mathematical tools to separate the steady starlight from these tiny planetary heat signatures, like isolating a whispered conversation in a noisy room. They tested their approach using computer simulations of three real planets that the James Webb Space Telescope could observe: a large hot planet, a medium-sized warm planet, and a smaller planet in the habitable zone around our nearest stellar neighbor, Proxima Centauri.
Key Findings
The simulations showed that VPIE can successfully distinguish between planets with different atmospheric behaviors—those that efficiently transport heat from day to night versus those that don't. The method can also estimate planetary sizes and temperatures without needing the planet to transit its star. While it works best for warmer planets that give off more infrared heat, the technique showed promise even for cooler, potentially habitable worlds.
Looking Forward
This breakthrough could dramatically expand our ability to study exoplanets, potentially opening up thousands of new worlds for investigation. Future improvements to the technique or more sensitive telescopes could make it possible to study the atmospheres of Earth-like planets around nearby stars, bringing us closer to answering whether we're alone in the universe.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RedDots: Multiplanet system around M dwarf GJ 887 in the solar neighborhood</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-08929v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-08929v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>C. Hartogh et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Finding planets around nearby stars isn't just an academic exercise—it's our best shot at discovering worlds that might harbor life. GJ 887, a small red star just 11 light-years from Earth, has become one of the most exciting planetary systems in our cosmic neighborhood. With multiple planets orbiting this dim but long-lived star, including one in the "Goldilocks zone" where liquid water could exist, this system offers a tantalizing glimpse of potentially habitable worlds practically next door in galactic terms.
What They Did
Astronomers used a clever detective technique to find these hidden planets. Since planets are too faint to see directly next to their bright parent stars, researchers instead watched for tiny wobbles in the star's motion. As planets orbit, their gravity tugs on their host star, causing it to move back and forth by mere meters per second—about walking speed. Using ultra-precise instruments called spectrographs at observatories in Chile, the team measured these minuscule stellar movements over many nights. The tricky part was separating genuine planet signals from the star's own natural variability, like stellar weather patterns. They used sophisticated computer modeling to filter out these stellar hiccups and reveal the gravitational signatures of orbiting worlds.
Key Findings
The team confirmed four planets around GJ 887, with a possible fifth awaiting verification. The most exciting discovery is a "super-Earth"—a rocky planet about twice our planet's mass—that orbits every 51 days in the habitable zone. This makes it the second-closest potentially habitable planet ever found, after Proxima Centauri b. The system also contains an Earth-mass planet whipping around its star every 4.4 days, plus two other confirmed worlds with 9-day and 22-day orbits. If the fifth planet candidate proves real, it would be smaller than Earth.
Looking Forward
This discovery transforms our understanding of planetary systems around red dwarf stars, which make up 75% of all stars in our galaxy. Having multiple planets so close to Earth makes GJ 887 a prime target for future space telescopes that might detect atmospheres or even signs of life on these distant worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST spectral retrieval of cold directly imaged planet WD0806 b and the first measurement of altitude-dependent Kzz in exoplanet atmospheres</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-08200v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-08200v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Ben W. P. Lew et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to study the atmosphere of a world so distant and cold that it's barely detectable—that's exactly what scientists have accomplished with WD0806 b, one of the most extreme planets we've ever observed. This frozen world orbits a dead star called a white dwarf at a staggering distance 2,500 times farther than Earth is from our Sun. At just 350 Kelvin (about 170°F), it's one of the coldest planets we can directly observe, making it a unique laboratory for understanding how planetary atmospheres work under extreme conditions. This research matters because it pushes the boundaries of what's possible in studying distant worlds and gives us insights into atmospheric physics that we simply can't get anywhere else.
What They Did
Using the James Webb Space Telescope—our most powerful space observatory—researchers captured both images and detailed light measurements of this frigid planet. Think of it like taking both a photograph and analyzing the "fingerprint" of light coming from the planet. Just as different materials absorb specific colors of light, different gases in the planet's atmosphere absorb specific wavelengths, creating a unique signature. The team developed new computer models to decode these light signatures, much like a detective analyzing clues to reconstruct what happened at a crime scene. They could then determine what gases are present and how the atmosphere moves and mixes at different altitudes.
Key Findings
The researchers made several groundbreaking discoveries. They found six different gases in the atmosphere—including water vapor, methane, and carbon monoxide—and measured how efficiently the atmosphere mixes at different heights. Surprisingly, mixing happens 100 times more vigorously deep in the atmosphere than at higher altitudes. The planet weighs about eight times more than Jupiter and has unusual chemistry: it's carbon-rich compared to our solar system's typical composition. This is the first time scientists have measured how atmospheric mixing changes with altitude on any exoplanet.
Looking Forward
This breakthrough demonstrates that we can now study atmospheric dynamics on distant worlds with unprecedented detail. These techniques will help us understand how weather and chemistry work on other planets, potentially including Earth-like worlds that might harbor life.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-Dimensional Kelvin-Helmholtz Instability with Anisotropic Pressure</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-08806v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-08806v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Shishir Biswas et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Space isn't empty—it's filled with hot, electrically charged gas called plasma that flows like invisible rivers throughout our solar system and beyond. When these cosmic streams move at different speeds, they create a phenomenon called the Kelvin-Helmholtz instability, which works like ocean waves forming where fast and slow currents meet. This process shapes everything from the boundaries of planetary magnetic fields to the swirling disks around newborn stars where planets form. Understanding how these cosmic "waves" behave helps us decode the fundamental physics governing star systems like our own and the distant worlds orbiting other stars.
What They Did
The researchers used computer simulations to study what happens when cosmic plasma streams flow past each other at different speeds, creating turbulent mixing zones. They compared two different scenarios: one where the plasma behaves like a simple fluid with uniform pressure in all directions, and another more realistic case where the pressure varies depending on direction—imagine a balloon that's easier to squeeze from the sides than from the top. By running these digital experiments with identical starting conditions but different physics rules, they could isolate exactly how pressure differences affect the cosmic wave formation.
Key Findings
The team discovered that when plasma pressure is uniform in all directions, it creates the most dramatic effects—stronger currents, larger swirling magnetic structures, and more chaotic mixing. When pressure becomes uneven, some energy gets "trapped" in maintaining these pressure differences rather than bending magnetic field lines, resulting in gentler, less turbulent behavior. This finding challenges assumptions about how violently these cosmic boundaries actually churn and mix.
Looking Forward
These results could reshape how we understand planetary system formation and evolution. The turbulent mixing at stream boundaries affects how material flows in planet-forming disks around young stars, potentially influencing where planets can form and what they're made of. For exoplanet hunters, this research provides better models for predicting the magnetic environments that might protect—or threaten—potentially habitable worlds orbiting distant stars.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
        <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
        <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
        <category>physics.space-ph</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Mass Constraints on Transition Disk Perturbers with the G23H Catalog</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-07731v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-07731v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dori Blakely et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to spot a firefly next to a stadium floodlight from miles away—that's essentially the challenge astronomers face when hunting for planets around other stars. Most exoplanets are discovered indirectly, but scientists desperately want to weigh these distant worlds to understand what they're made of and how they formed. This research represents a breakthrough in cosmic detective work, using the tiny wobbles that unseen companions cause in their host stars to reveal hidden planets and small stars in young solar systems still under construction.
What They Did
The researchers acted like cosmic motion detectors, using data from two European space telescopes—Hipparcos and Gaia—that precisely track star positions over decades. When a star has an orbiting companion, gravity causes both objects to dance around their shared center of mass, making the star appear to wiggle slightly in the sky. By measuring these incredibly subtle movements (imagine detecting motion smaller than the width of a human hair from 25 miles away), the team could infer the presence and mass of invisible companions. They focused on 11 young star systems surrounded by "transition disks"—dusty, planet-forming disks with suspicious gaps that might indicate hidden planets are carving out space as they orbit.
Key Findings
The cosmic hunt proved remarkably successful. The team found evidence for companions in seven of the 11 systems they studied, with rock-solid detections in three cases. They confirmed a known small star companion, discovered what's likely a "failed star" called a brown dwarf, and detected another mysterious companion that could be a massive planet. In systems where they found nothing, they could confidently rule out planets heavier than Jupiter within certain distances—like declaring a forest definitely has no elephants after a thorough search.
Looking Forward
This technique opens a new window into planet formation, potentially allowing astronomers to weigh planets while they're still growing in their dusty nurseries. Future space telescope data could reveal dozens more hidden worlds, transforming our understanding of how solar systems are born.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
