<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 03:29:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the Impact of Unresolved Stellar Companions on Detection Sensitivity in Kepler&#x27;s Small Planet Occurrence Rates</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16031v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-16031v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Galen J. Bergsten et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
For decades, astronomers have been trying to answer one of humanity's most profound questions: How common are Earth-like planets that could potentially harbor life? NASA's Kepler Space Telescope revolutionized this search by discovering thousands of planets orbiting distant stars. But there's been a hidden problem affecting our cosmic census—many stars that appear single actually have companion stars lurking nearby, invisible to Kepler's eyes. This stellar hide-and-seek has been quietly skewing our calculations about how many Earth-sized worlds exist in the "Goldilocks zone" where liquid water could survive. Getting these numbers right isn't just academic—it helps us understand whether Earth-like worlds are cosmic rarities or surprisingly common neighbors.
What They Did
The research team tackled this problem like cosmic detectives. They selected 198 stars from Kepler's catalog—stars that should be sensitive enough to spot Earth-like planets if they were truly alone in space. Then, using powerful ground-based telescopes equipped with adaptive optics (technology that removes atmospheric blur, like cosmic glasses), they took ultra-sharp images of each star. This technique can reveal companion stars that Kepler couldn't distinguish from the main star because they appear too close together. Think of it like using a magnifying glass to discover that what looked like one distant streetlight is actually two lights standing side by side. The team then ran computer simulations to account for even fainter companions their instruments couldn't detect, creating a complete picture of stellar multiplicity.
Key Findings
The results were eye-opening: one in five stars (20%) had hidden companions close enough to fool Kepler. These unseen stellar sidekicks were systematically throwing off planet measurements in two ways—making planets appear smaller than they actually are and making Kepler think it should have spotted planets more easily than it actually could. When the researchers corrected for these effects, they found that small planets are more common than previously thought. Most significantly, their calculations suggest Earth-sized planets in habitable zones are 18% to 46% more frequent than earlier estimates indicated.
Looking Forward
This discovery means the universe might be more planet-rich than we realized, particularly for worlds resembling our own. As next-generation telescopes like the James Webb Space Telescope begin studying planetary atmospheres, these refined occurrence rates will help astronomers better target their searches for potentially habitable worlds. The findings also highlight the importance of ground-based observations working hand-in-hand with space missions—sometimes the biggest discoveries come from looking more carefully at what we thought we already knew.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hot and cloudy: High temperature clouds in super-Earths and sub-Neptunes</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-15927v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-15927v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Leoni J. Janssen et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
For the first time, scientists have detected an atmosphere around a rocky planet outside our solar system—a milestone that brings us closer to understanding whether Earth-like worlds might harbor life. The planet, called 55 Cancri e, is what astronomers call a "super-Earth," roughly twice our planet's size but orbiting so close to its star that its surface reaches scorching temperatures of over 3,600°F. This discovery opens a new chapter in exoplanet research, showing we can now study the atmospheres of rocky worlds beyond our solar system and understand how planets form clouds under extreme conditions that don't exist anywhere in our solar system.
What They Did
Using NASA's powerful James Webb Space Telescope, researchers confirmed that 55 Cancri e has an atmosphere, then created detailed computer models to understand what kinds of clouds might form on such hellishly hot worlds. Think of it like creating a weather forecast, but for an alien planet where the "rain" might be made of titanium dioxide—the same compound found in sunscreen. They tested four different atmospheric recipes: atmospheres dominated by nitrogen (like Earth), oxygen, carbon, or hydrogen, then simulated how clouds would behave at temperatures between 1,300°F and 4,900°F—hot enough to melt copper.
Key Findings
The research revealed that a planet's ability to form clouds depends heavily on how much oxygen is in its atmosphere. Oxygen-rich atmospheres stay cooler and are excellent cloud factories, while oxygen-poor atmospheres get superheated by ultraviolet light, creating temperature inversions that prevent cloud formation—imagine trying to make rain in a furnace. On oxygen-rich super-Earths, the main cloud ingredient would be solid titanium dioxide, creating alien weather systems unlike anything on Earth. These clouds would be most visible when the planet passes in front of its star, blocking specific colors of light.
Looking Forward
This research provides astronomers with a roadmap for interpreting future observations of hot, rocky exoplanets. As the James Webb Space Telescope continues surveying these worlds, scientists will be able to identify cloud compositions and atmospheric types, bringing us closer to understanding how rocky planets evolve and potentially finding worlds with conditions suitable for life.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for stellar contamination and water absorption in NGTS-5b&#x27;s transmission spectra with GTC/OSIRIS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-15704v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-15704v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Wan-Hao Wang et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to study the air around a distant city by watching how its lights dim when clouds pass overhead. That's essentially what astronomers do when they study the atmospheres of planets orbiting other stars. These "exoplanets" offer our best chance to understand whether worlds like Earth—with breathable air and perhaps even life—might exist elsewhere in the universe. But there's a major challenge: the host stars themselves can play tricks on our observations, making it incredibly difficult to distinguish between what's actually in a planet's atmosphere versus contamination from the star's own surface features, like sunspots.
What They Did
Researchers focused on NGTS-5b, a planet roughly the size of Saturn but much closer to its star, making it quite warm. They used one of the world's largest telescopes—the 10.4-meter Gran Telescopio Canarias in Spain—to watch the planet pass in front of its star twice. As the planet crossed the star's face, some starlight filtered through the planet's atmosphere before reaching Earth. By carefully analyzing how different colors of light were absorbed during these transits, scientists could decode what gases might be floating in this distant world's air. They then used sophisticated computer models to interpret these cosmic fingerprints.
Key Findings
The team discovered strong evidence for water vapor in NGTS-5b's atmosphere—a crucial ingredient for life as we know it. The planet appears to have a relatively clear, thin atmosphere with low levels of heavy elements and an unusual carbon-to-oxygen ratio less than 22% of what we see in our Sun. However, the star itself proved problematic, with surface spots contaminating the observations and making the two transit measurements inconsistent with each other.
Looking Forward
This research highlights both the promise and challenges of studying exoplanet atmospheres. While the detection of water is exciting, the stellar contamination issue underscores why astronomers need multiple observations and better techniques to truly understand these distant worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
