<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 03:44:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Possible favored Great Oxidation Event scenario on exoplanets around M-Stars with the example of TRAPPIST-1e</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18324v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18324v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Adam Y. Jaziri, Nathalie Carrasco, Benjamin Charnay</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Earth's history includes a dramatic transformation that made complex life possible: the Great Oxidation Event. About 2.4 billion years ago, our planet's atmosphere suddenly filled with oxygen, paving the way for animals to eventually evolve. But this transition took hundreds of millions of years after oxygen-producing life first appeared, suggesting the process requires very specific conditions. Scientists have wondered whether planets orbiting other stars could undergo similar transformations—and if so, how we might detect them. This research explores whether Earth-like planets around the most common type of star in our galaxy, called M dwarfs, might actually have an easier path to developing oxygen-rich atmospheres than Earth did.
What They Did
The researchers used computer models to simulate the atmospheric evolution of TRAPPIST-1 e, a potentially habitable planet orbiting a red dwarf star about 40 light-years away. Think of it like creating a detailed weather forecast, but instead of predicting tomorrow's conditions, they're modeling how a planet's entire atmosphere might change over billions of years. They fed their model different scenarios for how oxygen could accumulate—either from photosynthetic life or from non-biological processes—and tracked how the atmosphere would respond. Their simulation account for the unique conditions around red dwarf stars, which emit different types of light than our Sun.
Key Findings
The results were striking: TRAPPIST-1 e could develop its oxygen revolution up to a billion years faster than Earth did. The key lies in ozone formation. The planet's star emits more ultraviolet light in certain wavelengths, which helps create ozone more efficiently from smaller amounts of oxygen. This ozone layer acts like a protective shield, allowing oxygen to build up in the atmosphere much more quickly. The researchers found that oxygen levels could rise high enough to support animal-like life forms in a fraction of the time it took on Earth.
Looking Forward
This research suggests that potentially habitable worlds around red dwarf stars—which make up about 75% of all stars—might be more likely to develop oxygen-rich atmospheres than previously thought. Even more exciting, the enhanced ozone production means the James Webb Space Telescope could detect these atmospheric signatures with far fewer observations than expected, possibly giving us our first glimpse of biological activity on distant worlds within the coming decade.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Intrinsic Temperature and Vertical Mixing in Characterizing Sub-Neptune Atmospheres</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18769v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18769v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Neha Dushyantha Kumar et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to figure out what's inside a wrapped gift just by weighing it and looking at its size. That's essentially the challenge astronomers face when studying sub-Neptune planets—worlds larger than Earth but smaller than Neptune that are among the most common planets in our galaxy. These mysterious worlds could be ocean planets with thin atmospheres, or rocky planets wrapped in thick blankets of hydrogen and helium gas. The difference matters enormously: it tells us whether Earth-like worlds with vast oceans might be common throughout the universe, potentially harboring life as we know it.
What They Did
The researchers used computer models to simulate the atmospheres of sub-Neptune planets, much like meteorologists model Earth's weather but for alien worlds. They focused on two critical factors that previous studies had largely ignored: the planet's internal heat (like a fever temperature from within) and how vigorously gases mix in the atmosphere (imagine stirring soup—some planets might have calm, layered atmospheres while others churn violently). Using advanced software, they created hundreds of different atmospheric scenarios, testing temperatures ranging from Antarctic-cold to oven-warm, and mixing rates spanning seven orders of magnitude. They then examined how these conditions would affect the chemical signatures we could detect with the James Webb Space Telescope.
Key Findings
The team discovered that a planet's internal temperature and atmospheric mixing dramatically change which molecules appear in its atmosphere. Methane, carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide, ammonia, and hydrogen cyanide levels varied significantly across different scenarios, while water vapor remained relatively stable. Most importantly, they found that making simple assumptions about these factors—as previous studies had done—could lead scientists to completely misidentify what these planets are made of, potentially mistaking a rocky world for an ocean planet or vice versa.
Looking Forward
This research provides astronomers with a new toolkit for interpreting observations from the James Webb Space Telescope. By considering the full range of possible atmospheric conditions rather than making simplified assumptions, scientists can now make more accurate determinations about whether sub-Neptune planets are ocean worlds or rocky planets with thick atmospheres. This improved understanding brings us closer to answering one of astronomy's biggest questions: how common are potentially habitable worlds in our galaxy?]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atmospheric Circulation of High-Obliquity Mini-Neptunes</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18606v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-18606v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Yanhong Lai, Xianyu Tan, Yubo Su</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine a planet tilted so far on its side that it essentially rolls around its star instead of spinning like a top. Scientists have discovered that some distant worlds called mini-Neptunes—planets larger than Earth but smaller than Neptune—might be tilted at extreme angles, creating bizarre weather patterns unlike anything in our solar system. With NASA's powerful James Webb Space Telescope now able to study the atmospheres of these far-off worlds, we're getting our first glimpse of truly alien meteorology. Understanding these tilted planets helps us grasp the incredible diversity of worlds beyond our solar system and challenges our assumptions about how planetary atmospheres behave.
What They Did
Researchers used computer simulations to model the weather patterns on K2-290 b, a mini-Neptune located about 897 light-years away that may be tilted at a dramatic 67-degree angle (imagine Earth tilted so far that the North Pole points toward the sun during summer). They created detailed three-dimensional models of the planet's atmosphere, like sophisticated weather forecasting software, to predict wind patterns, temperature distributions, and seasonal changes. The team ran different scenarios—some assuming the planet always shows the same face to its star (like our Moon does to Earth), and others where it rotates independently while orbiting.
Key Findings
The simulations revealed that these tilted mini-Neptunes develop remarkably uniform temperatures across their surfaces, with only moderate hot and cold spots. When the planet is locked to show one side to its star, powerful eastward winds create a "superrotation" that efficiently spreads heat around the globe. For freely rotating tilted planets, the researchers discovered something extraordinary: the atmosphere oscillates in roughly 70-day cycles, creating a complex seasonal pattern driven by the extreme tilt. These weather signals would be detectable by our best telescopes, though the signatures are subtle—about 100 parts per million in atmospheric measurements.
Looking Forward
This research opens a new frontier in exoplanet science, showing that worlds can have atmospheric behaviors far more exotic than previously imagined. As the James Webb Space Telescope continues observing mini-Neptunes, astronomers now know what signatures to look for when hunting for these dramatically tilted worlds, potentially revealing an entire class of planets with seasons and weather patterns that would make science fiction writers envious.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timescales diagnostics for saving viscous and MHD-driven dusty discs from external photoevaporation</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-13200v2</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2601-13200v2</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Pichierri et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to build a sandcastle while ocean waves constantly wash away your progress. That's essentially what happens when planets try to form around young stars—they need enough time and material to come together before powerful stellar radiation blows everything away. This research tackles one of astronomy's biggest puzzles: how do planets manage to form at all? Understanding this process helps us explain not only how our own Solar System came to be, but also why we see such incredible diversity among the thousands of exoplanets discovered orbiting other stars. The answer lies in the delicate dance between the forces that help planetary building blocks survive and those that destroy them.
What They Did
The researchers created computer simulations of protoplanetary discs—the spinning pancakes of gas and dust that surround newborn stars and serve as planet-forming nurseries. They tested different scenarios to see what happens when these discs face various challenges. Think of it like testing different recipes under different conditions: some discs spread outward due to internal friction (like honey slowly spreading on toast), others are pushed around by magnetic forces (like iron filings near a magnet), and some experience both effects. Meanwhile, they subjected these virtual discs to different levels of harsh ultraviolet radiation from nearby massive stars—the cosmic equivalent of a blowtorch trying to evaporate the disc material.
Key Findings
The team discovered that a disc's survival depends on a crucial balance between two competing factors: its ability to spread outward and the strength of destructive radiation it faces. Surprisingly, discs driven by magnetic winds, while better protected from radiation damage, don't actually live longer than those evolving through friction. At high radiation levels, it doesn't matter which mechanism drives the disc—they all face similar lifetimes. For the dust particles that eventually become planets, the biggest threats are drifting inward toward the star and being swept away by radiation-driven winds.
Looking Forward
These findings suggest that planet formation requires more than just the right balance of forces—it likely needs special structures within discs to trap and protect planet-building materials. This research provides a roadmap for understanding why some stellar systems successfully form planets while others remain barren, ultimately helping us piece together the cosmic story of how worlds like Earth come to exist.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
