<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 04:17:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Extragalactic Exoplanets: A Survey of the Sagittarius Dwarf Galaxy Stream with TESS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15105v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15105v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>William Schap, Jason Dittmann, Elizabeth Lada</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
For decades, astronomers have discovered thousands of planets orbiting stars in our own galaxy, the Milky Way. But what about planets in other galaxies entirely? This groundbreaking research represents humanity's first systematic attempt to find planets beyond our galactic neighborhood—a quest that could reveal whether planetary systems are truly universal phenomena or if conditions in different galaxies produce dramatically different results. The answer could fundamentally change our understanding of how common planets are in the universe and whether the building blocks of life exist everywhere or just in special cosmic neighborhoods like our own.
What They Did
The researchers turned their attention to the Sagittarius dwarf galaxy, a smaller galaxy that's currently being torn apart and absorbed by our Milky Way. They used NASA's planet-hunting telescope TESS (Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite) to monitor over 15,000 stars from this disrupted galaxy. Like celestial detectives, they watched for tiny, periodic dips in starlight that occur when a planet crosses in front of its host star—imagine watching for the shadow of a fly passing in front of a distant lighthouse. They specifically searched for "hot Jupiters"—massive planets that orbit extremely close to their stars, completing their years in just days rather than the 11 years our Jupiter takes.
Key Findings
Despite monitoring thousands of stars, the team found exactly zero planets. While this might seem disappointing, it's actually scientifically valuable information. Based on their observations, they calculated that fewer than 1% of stars in this extragalactic stream likely host hot Jupiter planets. This rate appears even lower than what's been observed in ancient star clusters within our own galaxy, suggesting that stars from different galactic environments might indeed have fewer large planets.
Looking Forward
This research blazes the trail for extragalactic planet hunting. The team estimates that monitoring over 11,000 additional extragalactic stars could either yield the first confirmed planet from another galaxy or provide strong evidence that older, metal-poor galactic environments simply don't produce as many giant planets as our relatively young, metal-rich Milky Way does.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper atmosphere dynamics and drivers of volatiles loss from terrestrial-type (exo)planets</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15507v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15507v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Daria Kubyshkina et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[# Could Earth-like Worlds Around Smaller Stars Keep Their Air?
Why It Matters
Imagine finding a planet that looks just like Earth—the right size, the right distance from its star, potentially the right conditions for liquid water. But what if that planet has no atmosphere at all? This research tackles one of the biggest questions in our search for life beyond Earth: whether planets orbiting smaller, dimmer stars can actually hold onto the air that makes life possible. Since most of the potentially habitable worlds we've discovered orbit these smaller stars rather than Sun-like ones, understanding atmospheric loss could determine whether we're looking for life in the right places—or if these worlds are actually barren, airless rocks.
What They Did
The researchers studied how planets lose their atmospheres by examining what happens in the upper layers of planetary air, where space meets atmosphere. Think of it like studying how a hot cup of coffee loses steam—but instead of water vapor escaping, entire atmospheres can be stripped away by intense radiation from nearby stars. They compared conditions around different types of stars: our Sun (a medium-sized G-dwarf), and the smaller, cooler K-dwarf and M-dwarf stars that most Earth-like exoplanets orbit. They analyzed how X-ray and ultraviolet radiation from these stars affects planetary atmospheres over billions of years.
Key Findings
The research reveals a cosmic catch-22. While smaller M-dwarf and K-dwarf stars are dimmer overall, planets must orbit much closer to them to stay warm enough for liquid water—sometimes ten times closer than Earth orbits the Sun. At these close distances, planets receive intense X-ray and ultraviolet bombardment that can blast away their atmospheres. Making matters worse, these smaller stars stay active and energetic for billions of years longer than Sun-like stars, potentially stripping atmospheres throughout a planet's entire lifetime.
Looking Forward
This research highlights the central debate in exoplanet science: are most potentially habitable worlds actually uninhabitable? The answer depends on whether these planets started with thick enough atmospheres to survive the bombardment, or whether they can replenish lost air through volcanic activity. Future space telescopes will test these predictions by directly measuring the atmospheres of nearby exoplanets, finally revealing whether our cosmic neighbors have managed to keep their air.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise measurement of WASP-31 b&#x27;s Rossiter-McLaughlin effect and characterization of the planet transmission spectra</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15501v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15501v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>M. Steiner et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to analyze the air quality in a distant city by studying how sunlight changes as it passes through the atmosphere—except the city is orbiting another star 1,200 light-years away. That's essentially what astronomers are attempting when they study exoplanet atmospheres. WASP-31 b, a "hot Jupiter" roughly the size of our solar system's largest planet but scorching hot from orbiting extremely close to its star, offers a perfect natural laboratory for understanding alien worlds. These atmospheric studies could eventually help us identify planets with conditions suitable for life, making this research a crucial stepping stone toward answering whether we're alone in the universe.
What They Did
Using one of the world's most advanced telescopes in Chile, researchers observed WASP-31 b as it passed in front of its host star multiple times. Think of it like watching a soap bubble drift across a flashlight beam—the light changes slightly as it filters through the bubble, revealing what the bubble is made of. The team used an ultra-precise instrument called ESPRESSO to split the starlight into its component colors, creating a cosmic fingerprint. They also measured how the planet's orbit affects the star's rotation, like watching a spotlight wobble slightly as an object passes in front of it. The challenge was separating the planet's faint atmospheric signature from much stronger contamination caused by the star's own light.
Key Findings
The researchers confirmed that WASP-31 b orbits almost perfectly aligned with its star's equator, with a tilt of just -0.09 degrees—imagine a coin spinning on a table that's nearly perfectly flat. However, they couldn't detect any specific chemicals in the planet's atmosphere, including potassium and chromium hydride that other studies had previously identified. This wasn't necessarily because these substances aren't there, but because contamination from the star's own light was too overwhelming, like trying to hear a whisper next to a roaring waterfall.
Looking Forward
This study highlights a major challenge facing exoplanet science: current technology struggles to separate planetary atmospheric signals from stellar contamination, especially for planets in well-aligned orbits like WASP-31 b. However, this limitation is temporary. Next-generation telescopes currently under construction will be dramatically more powerful, potentially overcoming these obstacles and opening a new era of detailed atmospheric analysis of distant worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Axion-like particle Dark Matter with Time-domain Polarization: Constraints from a protoplanetary disk</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15611v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15611v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Kanako Narita et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Scientists are hunting for one of the universe's greatest mysteries: dark matter, the invisible substance that makes up most of our cosmos. While we can't see dark matter directly, it might reveal itself by subtly twisting starlight as it travels through space—like how polarized sunglasses filter light in a specific direction. Researchers have now turned to young solar systems still forming around distant stars, using these cosmic nurseries as natural laboratories to search for dark matter's fingerprints in polarized light.
What They Did
The team studied HD 163296, a young star surrounded by a swirling disk of gas and dust where planets are likely forming—similar to how our own solar system looked billions of years ago. Using powerful telescopes, they measured how light from this disk was polarized (oriented in specific directions) and tracked these measurements across six different observations over roughly a year. Think of it like taking multiple photos of the same scene with polarized sunglasses, then checking if the light's orientation changed between shots. If hypothetical particles called axion-like particles—a leading dark matter candidate—exist, they should cause this polarized light to slowly rotate over time, like a cosmic polarizing filter spinning in space.
Key Findings
The polarized light showed no detectable rotation over the 170-400 day observation period, remaining steady within measurement uncertainties of about 1.6 to 6.4 degrees. While this might sound like a null result, it actually provides valuable constraints—the researchers could rule out certain types of dark matter particles and set the first-ever limits on how strongly these hypothetical particles interact with light using data from planet-forming disks.
Looking Forward
This technique opens an entirely new window for dark matter detection using the numerous planet-forming disks astronomers observe. With more precise measurements—achieving uncertainties of just 0.1 degrees—future observations could provide world-leading sensitivity to dark matter, potentially solving one of physics' biggest puzzles while simultaneously studying how planetary systems form.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>hep-ph</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Montreal Open Clusters and Associations (MOCA) Database: A Census of Nearby Associations, Open Clusters, and Young Substellar Objects within 500 pc of the Sun</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15695v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15695v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Gagné et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to determine someone's age just by looking at them—it's tricky, right? The same challenge exists when studying planets orbiting other stars. To truly understand how planets form and evolve, astronomers need to know their ages. The key lies in studying young star clusters and associations—cosmic neighborhoods where stars are born together and share the same age. This research creates the most comprehensive catalog yet of these stellar neighborhoods near Earth, opening new windows into planetary science and helping us understand how planetary systems like our own come to be.
What They Did
Researchers built a massive digital library called the Montreal Open Clusters and Associations database, or MOCAdb for short. Think of it as a cosmic census that catalogs over 10,000 star groups within 500 light-years of Earth—our local galactic neighborhood. They gathered information from hundreds of scientific papers, recording everything from star types to how fast they spin. The team also improved a tool called BANYAN Σ (pronounced "sigma"), which works like facial recognition software for stars, identifying which cosmic neighborhood each star belongs to by analyzing how it moves through space.
Key Findings
The database revealed some exciting discoveries. The researchers identified nearly 11,500 previously unknown candidate members of young star groups, mostly small, dim stars called M dwarfs. They cataloged 134 planetary systems with known ages, plus 121 potential new ones spotted by NASA's planet-hunting telescope TESS. Perhaps most intriguingly, they found 101 "rogue" objects that appear to be planet-sized but float freely through space without orbiting any star—cosmic orphans that challenge our understanding of how planets form.
Looking Forward
This treasure trove of data will revolutionize exoplanet science. With precise ages for these stellar neighborhoods, astronomers can now study how planets change over millions of years, track atmospheric evolution, and better understand which types of planets might harbor life. It's like having a cosmic time machine that lets us see planets at different stages of their lives.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
