<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 04:16:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>The Radius Cliff is a Waterfall: Explaining Sub-Neptune Exoplanets with Steam Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11923v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11923v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Aritra Chakrabarty et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[# Scientists Discover "Steam Worlds" May Explain Missing Link in Planetary Evolution
Why It Matters
For years, astronomers have puzzled over a mysterious gap in the sizes of planets beyond our solar system. While we find plenty of small, rocky "super-Earths" and larger "sub-Neptunes" with thick atmospheres, there's a conspicuous shortage of planets in between—roughly twice Earth's size. Understanding this "radius valley" is crucial because it reveals how planets form and evolve, helping us piece together the story of planetary systems throughout the galaxy. This research suggests we may have been looking at the problem all wrong.
What They Did
The researchers analyzed data from NASA's Kepler Space Telescope, which discovered thousands of exoplanets by watching them cross in front of their stars. Instead of assuming this size gap resulted from planets losing their atmospheres over time, the team explored whether different types of planets—rocky worlds versus water-rich "steam worlds"—could naturally create this pattern. They built computer models of planets made largely of water, with steamy atmospheres created by their own heated surfaces, and compared these to the actual planets Kepler discovered.
Key Findings
The models revealed that water worlds with steam atmospheres can perfectly reproduce the observed size gap around twice Earth's radius. These steam worlds appear to make up a significant portion of sub-Neptune planets, with water comprising about 41% of their mass on average. The research suggests the "radius cliff" is actually more like a "waterfall"—a sharp drop-off where steam worlds become much rarer. However, the largest sub-Neptunes (over three times Earth's radius) still need traditional hydrogen and helium atmospheres to explain their size.
Looking Forward
This discovery fundamentally reshapes our understanding of planetary diversity. Rather than viewing the size gap as planets losing atmospheres, we may be seeing two distinct families of worlds that formed differently from the start. This could help astronomers better predict what types of planets exist around other stars and refine our search for potentially habitable worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global magnetohydrodynamic simulations of the inner regions of protoplanetary discs. II. Vertical-net-flux regime</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11818v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11818v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Matthew J. O. Roberts, Henrik N. Latter, Geoffroy Lesur</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[# Scientists Reveal How Baby Solar Systems Shape the Worlds Where Life Might Emerge
Why It Matters
When stars are born, they're surrounded by spinning disks of gas and dust—the cosmic nurseries where planets form. The inner parts of these disks, roughly where Earth sits in our solar system, are where rocky planets like ours could potentially harbor life. But these regions are incredibly chaotic, with powerful magnetic forces and swirling material creating conditions that directly influence what kinds of worlds emerge. Understanding these early environments helps us predict where habitable planets might form around other stars and what they might look like when they do.
What They Did
Researchers created detailed computer simulations of these planet-forming disks, focusing on the boundary between two very different zones. Think of it like the edge between a stormy ocean and calm waters—one region is turbulent and electrically active (like a thunderstorm), while the other is quiet and electrically "dead." The scientists ran five separate simulations, each tracking how magnetic fields, gas flows, and electrical currents behave across this boundary over time. They included realistic physics for how electricity flows through the disk and how heat moves between the cool disk and the hot atmosphere above it.
Key Findings
The simulations revealed that this boundary acts like a one-way gate, trapping magnetic field lines and preventing them from moving inward. This creates a magnetic traffic jam that leads to dramatic variability—imagine electrical currents trying to flow smoothly across two completely different environments. Surprisingly, the researchers found continuous outflows of material (stellar winds) across the entire disk, rather than distinct zones. They also discovered that vortices form at the boundary, similar to atmospheric storms, which could influence how planets form and migrate.
Looking Forward
These findings reshape our understanding of where and how Earth-like planets form. The magnetic barriers and variable conditions in these regions could determine whether forming planets develop protective magnetic fields and retain their atmospheres—crucial factors for habitability. This research provides a more accurate foundation for predicting which of the thousands of known exoplanets might truly be capable of supporting life.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oxygen left behind: Atmospheric Enrichment due to Fractionation in Sub-Neptunes using BOREAS</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12201v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-12201v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Marilina Valatsou et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine if Earth's atmosphere could completely transform over millions of years, turning from one type of air into something entirely different. That's exactly what's happening to planets beyond our solar system. Scientists have discovered that many Earth-sized and Neptune-sized planets are literally losing their atmospheres to space—but not all gases escape equally. This selective loss could be creating worlds with dramatically different compositions than when they first formed, potentially leading to planets rich in water vapor where none existed before. Understanding this process helps us figure out which distant worlds might be habitable and reveals how planetary atmospheres evolve over cosmic time.
What They Did
The research team built a sophisticated computer model called BOREAS to simulate how planets lose their atmospheres. Think of it like modeling how a pot of soup boils away—but instead of just water evaporating, different ingredients escape at different rates. Their model tracks two key components: hydrogen (the lightest element) and oxygen (much heavier). They tested this simulation across hundreds of different planetary scenarios, varying factors like planet size, distance from the host star, and how much high-energy radiation the planet receives. By running these virtual experiments, they could watch how atmospheric composition changes over millions of years.
Key Findings
The results reveal a cosmic sorting process: hydrogen escapes to space much more easily than oxygen, leaving planets with increasingly oxygen-rich atmospheres over time. Planets can become substantially enriched in heavier gases within about 200 million years—a blink of an eye in cosmic terms. However, this process only works under specific conditions. Too much stellar radiation strips away everything, while too little fails to drive significant atmospheric loss. The sweet spot creates planets that could end up with water-rich atmospheres, even if they started water-poor.
Looking Forward
This research suggests that many planets we observe today may be atmospheric shape-shifters, bearing little resemblance to their original compositions. Some sub-Neptune planets near Earth's size might have evolved into water worlds, offering new targets in our search for potentially habitable environments beyond our solar system.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gas-depleted planet formation occurred in the four-planet system around the red dwarf LHS 1903</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11271v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11271v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Thomas G. Wilson et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Scientists have long wondered how planets get their "clothes"—the atmospheres that wrap around rocky cores. Some planets are naked rocks, while others wear thick gaseous coats. This discovery helps solve that puzzle by finding a rare planetary family where we can see both types living around the same star. Understanding how atmospheres form and disappear is crucial because it determines whether a planet could potentially support life as we know it.
What They Did
The research team played cosmic detective, using two main tools to study a small red star called LHS 1903. First, they watched for tiny dips in the star's brightness—like detecting a fly crossing in front of a streetlight—which happens when planets pass between us and their star. Second, they measured how the star wobbles slightly as its planets tug on it gravitationally, like a dog walker being pulled by four different dogs. By combining these techniques, they could determine each planet's size, weight, and density.
Key Findings
The team discovered four planets with dramatically different personalities orbiting their red dwarf star every 2.2 to 29.3 days. The innermost planet is a dense, rocky world stripped bare of atmosphere. Two middle planets retained thick, puffy atmospheres that make them larger despite potentially having similar rocky cores. Most surprisingly, the outermost planet—which should have been the easiest to keep an atmosphere in the cooler outer regions—is completely naked rock. This suggests it never had an atmosphere to begin with, forming from material that was already stripped of gas.
Looking Forward
This planetary system serves as a natural laboratory for understanding how planets acquire and lose their atmospheres. The surprising naked outer planet suggests that the disk of gas and dust from which these planets formed was already depleted, offering new insights into planetary formation around red dwarf stars—the most common type in our galaxy.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eccentricity Evolution of Warm Jupiters: The Role of Distant Perturbers and Nearby Companions</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11531v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-11531v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Ying He, Dong-Hong Wu, Sheng Jin</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine discovering that planets the size of Jupiter orbit other stars much closer to their suns than Jupiter orbits ours—but not as close as scorching "hot Jupiters" that whip around their stars in just days. These "warm Jupiters" represent a cosmic mystery that's been puzzling astronomers: why do some have stretched-out, oval-shaped orbits while others follow nearly perfect circles? Understanding how these giant worlds ended up in their current positions helps us piece together the chaotic story of how planetary systems form and evolve—including whether systems like ours are common or rare in the galaxy.
What They Did
The researchers created detailed computer simulations—like cosmic video games—to watch how warm Jupiters behave over millions of years. They populated virtual solar systems with different combinations of planets: the warm Jupiter itself, smaller "super-Earth" planets nearby, and distant giant planets acting as gravitational bullies. By running these simulations thousands of times with different starting conditions, they could observe how the orbits changed over time and compare the results to real exoplanets we've discovered.
Key Findings
The team discovered a cosmic tug-of-war that explains warm Jupiters' varied orbits. When distant giant planets act alone, they can dramatically stretch a warm Jupiter's orbit through a gravitational effect called the von Zeipel-Lidov-Kozai mechanism—essentially a rhythmic gravitational squeeze that makes orbits more oval over time. However, nearby super-Earth companions act like protective siblings, their gravity dampening these wild orbital swings and keeping warm Jupiters on more circular paths. This creates two distinct populations: warm Jupiters with nearby planetary neighbors tend to have calm, circular orbits, while lone warm Jupiters show much more varied, eccentric paths.
Looking Forward
This research suggests that planetary systems undergo dramatic reshuffling long after their initial formation, like cosmic musical chairs that can last millions of years. These findings will help astronomers better interpret observations from current and future planet-hunting missions, potentially revealing which planetary systems experienced violent histories versus more peaceful evolution—crucial insights for understanding where Earth-like worlds might thrive.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
