<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
    <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    <description>Daily summaries of exoplanet research papers from arXiv astro-ph.EP, written for general audiences.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 04:15:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <image>
      <url>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv/icon.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Papers | Daily arXiv Summaries</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Planet-Disk Interactions and the Convective Overstability. I. Low Mass Planets</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15978v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15978v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>M. Lehmann, M. K. Lin</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine you're building a sandcastle right at the water's edge—the waves keep washing away your work before you can finish. Baby planets face a similar problem in the swirling disks of gas and dust around young stars. These newborn worlds tend to spiral inward toward their host stars so quickly that they should be destroyed before they can grow into the diverse array of planets we observe today. Yet somehow, planets do survive and thrive. This research tackles one of astronomy's biggest puzzles: how do small planets avoid this deadly spiral and live long enough to become the rocky worlds like Earth that populate our universe?
What They Did
The researchers created detailed computer simulations of protoplanetary disks—the spinning pancakes of material around young stars where planets form. Think of these simulations like sophisticated weather models, but instead of predicting rain, they track how gas swirls around and interacts with embedded baby planets. They ran both simplified 2D versions (like looking at the disk from the side) and more complex 3D models that included realistic heating and cooling effects. By comparing these different approaches, they could isolate what happens when the disk develops a particular type of instability called the Convective Overstability, which creates large, persistent whirlpools in the gas.
Key Findings
The simulations revealed that these cosmic whirlpools act like lifeguards for baby planets. When the swirling vortices encounter a small planet, they typically give it a gravitational "kick" outward, counteracting the inward death spiral. This effect can extend a planet's survival time by roughly 10 times—potentially allowing planets to live for 0.1 to 5 million years, which gives them enough time to grow into "Super-Earths" (planets larger than Earth but smaller than Neptune). Without these helpful vortices, planets would spiral into their stars in just tens of thousands of years.
Looking Forward
This discovery suggests that the chaotic, turbulent environment of planet formation might actually help planets survive rather than destroy them. It provides a potential solution to the long-standing mystery of why we see so many planets in the universe when theory suggests they should have been consumed by their stars long ago. Future observations of young planetary systems may be able to detect these protective vortices directly, giving us new insights into how planetary systems like our own solar system came to be.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two warm sub-Saturn mass planets identified from the TESS Full Frame Images</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-16646v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-16646v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Felipe I. Rojas et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[# Scientists Discover Two Mysterious "Sub-Saturn" Worlds That Challenge Planet Formation Theories
Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand how cars are built by only studying vehicles parked in your neighborhood. That's similar to the challenge astronomers face when studying how planets form—we've been limited to our own solar system for most of human history. Every new planet we discover around other stars is like finding a completely different type of vehicle, giving us clues about the cosmic "assembly line" that creates worlds. These two newly discovered planets are particularly intriguing because they're caught in a cosmic mystery: despite being remarkably similar in many ways, they appear to have completely different internal structures, suggesting the universe has multiple recipes for building planets.
What They Did
The research team used NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), a space telescope that acts like a cosmic detective, watching for the tiny dimming that occurs when planets cross in front of their host stars. Think of it like watching someone walk in front of a streetlight—the light briefly dims, revealing the person's presence. Once TESS spotted these planetary shadows, astronomers used ground-based telescopes to measure how the planets' gravity tugs on their stars, causing them to wobble slightly. By combining these techniques—like measuring both a person's shadow and how much they make a seesaw tip—scientists could determine each planet's size and weight.
Key Findings
The two planets, designated TOI-883 b and TOI-899 b, are both "sub-Saturns"—meaning they're smaller than Saturn but larger than Neptune. TOI-883 b weighs about 12% as much as Jupiter but is surprisingly compact, while TOI-899 b is nearly twice as heavy but much puffier, almost Jupiter's size. Both orbit their Sun-like stars in roughly 10-13 days, making them scorching hot worlds with temperatures around 1,040-1,086 Kelvin (about 1,400-1,500°F). Despite their similar masses and orbital characteristics, their dramatically different densities suggest they're made of different materials entirely.
Looking Forward
These planets represent perfect laboratories for testing our theories about how worlds form. Their similar orbits but different compositions suggest that planetary formation might be more varied and complex than we previously thought. Because they're relatively close to Earth and orbit bright stars, future telescopes will be able to analyze their atmospheres in detail, potentially revealing whether one formed closer to its star while the other migrated inward, or whether they represent entirely different planetary formation pathways in the vast cosmic cookbook.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiwavelength Campaign Observations of a Young Solar-type Star, EK Draconis. III. Comparison between Starspot Mapping, Zeeman Doppler Imaging, and Multiwavelength Variability</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15979v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-15979v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Kai Ikuta et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine if our Sun suddenly unleashed a solar flare thousands of times more powerful than anything we've ever recorded—that's what scientists call a "superflare." While our middle-aged Sun is relatively well-behaved, younger stars like EK Draconis regularly produce these monster eruptions that could strip away a planet's atmosphere entirely. Understanding these stellar tantrums is crucial because they help us predict which exoplanets might still have the protective atmospheres needed to support life. By studying this young, Sun-like star located just 111 light-years away, researchers are essentially looking back in time to see what our own solar system was like 4.5 billion years ago.
What They Did
The research team conducted an ambitious stellar surveillance operation, monitoring EK Draconis simultaneously with multiple types of telescopes and instruments. They used NASA's planet-hunting TESS satellite to track brightness changes as dark spots rotated across the star's surface—like watching sunspots, but much larger. Meanwhile, they employed a technique called Zeeman Doppler Imaging, which reads the magnetic fingerprints in starlight to map the star's invisible magnetic field. They also observed the star in X-ray light and through a specific red wavelength called H-alpha, which reveals activity in the star's upper atmosphere. This multi-pronged approach allowed them to build a comprehensive picture of how the star's surface features, magnetic fields, and atmospheric eruptions all connect.
Key Findings
The team discovered that their different observation methods painted remarkably consistent pictures of where active regions exist on the star's surface. The dark spots visible in ordinary light lined up almost perfectly with the magnetic field maps, confirming that these features are intimately connected. They found that eruptions in the star's upper atmosphere follow a clear rhythm that matches the star's 2.6-day rotation period, suggesting these explosive events are tied to specific active regions spinning in and out of view. However, X-ray observations showed more chaotic patterns, likely because the star's outer atmosphere is so violently active that multiple overlapping events obscure any simple relationship.
Looking Forward
This research provides a crucial missing piece in understanding how stellar radiation affects planetary atmospheres. By connecting a star's magnetic activity to its high-energy output, scientists can better predict which exoplanets might retain their atmospheres over billions of years—a key requirement for habitability.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
        <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Photolysis Rates with Socrates (24.11): Species for Earth and Exoplanets</title>
      <link>https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-16453v1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://arifsolmaz.github.io/arxiv#paper-2602-16453v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Sophia M. Adams et al.</dc:creator>
      <description><![CDATA[Why It Matters
Imagine trying to understand how a recipe works without knowing what happens when you mix the ingredients. That's the challenge scientists face when studying atmospheres on distant planets called exoplanets. When starlight hits a planet's atmosphere, it breaks apart molecules in a process called photolysis—like how sunlight can fade your car's paint over time, but much more dramatic. Understanding these reactions is crucial because they determine whether a planet could support life, what gases we might detect in its atmosphere, and how similar or different it might be from Earth. This research helps scientists decode the "chemical recipes" happening in alien skies.
What They Did
The researchers used a sophisticated computer program called Socrates to calculate how quickly different molecules break apart when hit by light from two types of stars: our Sun and smaller, cooler stars called M dwarfs. Think of it like figuring out how fast different materials would dissolve under different colored lights. They tested their calculations against previous scientific work to make sure their results were accurate, similar to how a chef might compare their recipe against a trusted cookbook. They examined dozens of different atmospheric molecules, including some found in Earth's air and others that might exist in the exotic atmospheres of distant worlds.
Key Findings
The team discovered that planets orbiting M dwarf stars—the most common type of star in our galaxy—experience much more intense molecular breakup than Earth does. M dwarfs emit more high-energy ultraviolet light, which acts like a stronger "molecular sledgehammer" compared to our gentler Sun. This means atmospheres around these stars undergo faster and more dramatic chemical changes. The researchers also found that their new calculations largely agreed with previous work, but revealed some important differences when accounting for how temperature and pressure affect these reactions.
Looking Forward
This research provides scientists with a crucial toolkit for interpreting observations from space telescopes like the James Webb Space Telescope. When we detect gases in exoplanet atmospheres, understanding photolysis rates helps determine whether we're seeing a stable atmosphere or one being rapidly transformed by its star's radiation—critical information in the search for potentially habitable worlds.]]></description>
        <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
